<resources>
    <string name="app_name">Natural Medicine</string>

    <string name="aceptar">ACCEPT</string>

    <string name="advert">Warning</string>
    <string name="advertencia">This application is not a guide to self-medicate or to replace medicines. The doses and modes of application are general, and therefore, they do not contemplate allergic reactions or reactions specific to each person. The uses presented here are based on the tradition that has been passed down from generation to generation. in generation constituting a naturalistic popular culture. It is important to establish that plants usually have names different in each region and that even the same name can be given to Various species. We are not responsible for problems caused by the misuse of the information presented or by the erroneous identification that the user makes of any of the medicinal plants discussed here.</string>

    <string name="app_id" translatable="false">ca-app-pub-6420027936185714~4539994516</string>

    <string name="banner1" translatable="false">ca-app-pub-6420027936185714/3226912847</string>
    <string name="banner2" translatable="false">ca-app-pub-6420027936185714/7442130658</string>
    <string name="banner3" translatable="false">ca-app-pub-6420027936185714/2719468774</string>

    <string name="categorias_w">Terms used</string>
    <string name="cient_w">Scientific name</string>
    <string name="dolen">Ailments</string>

    <string name="favoritos">Favorites</string>
    <string name="favs">Favorite Plants</string>

    <string name="inicio">Home</string>
    <string name="inter" translatable="false">ca-app-pub-6420027936185714/1214815416</string>
    <string name="medic_load" translatable="false">ca-app-pub-6420027936185714/2492033447</string>
    <string name="modo_w">Mode of use and preparation</string>
    <string name="nativo" translatable="false">ca-app-pub-6420027936185714/4061877472</string>
    <string name="organo_w">Organ or part of the plant used</string>
    <string name="prepa">Prepared</string>
    <string name="rateus">Value us</string>
    <string name="remedies">Remedies</string>
    <string name="usos_w">Traditional uses</string>
    <string name="share">Share</string>

    <array name="caracteristicas">
        <item>Nombre Científico:Allium cepa L.# Nombre Común:Onion# Órgano o parte de la planta usada:Bulbs and leaves.# Usos más comunes:Cardiocirculatory, protector of small vessels, diuretic, disinfectant in the digestive system; It is carminative and expectorant, so it is useful in respiratory conditions (bronchitis, laryngitis and asthma). It stimulates liver functions, is useful in kidney and urinary tract conditions, as well as strengthens bones and acts against rheumatism . It also has a healing function on the skin.# Modo de uso y preparación:It acts through its ingestion in meals, but decoctions, tinctures and creams are generally prepared, the latter effective for skin healing.# Categorias:4,10,39,40,42,64,70,87#</item>
        <item>Nombre Científico:Allium sativum L.# Nombre Común:Garlic# Órgano o parte de la planta usada:Fresh bulbs.# Usos más comunes:Expectorant; it is used as a general antiseptic, especially for fungal and bacterial infections, as well as a vermifuge; It is recognized as action against diabetes, asthma, to lower fever, blood pressure, cholesterol levels; stimulates gastric and bile secretions and also protects against cancer and arteriosclerosis.# Modo de uso y preparación:The teeth are used, which are eaten whole or crushed, or the oil resulting from frying them is taken, especially for rheumatism. They also have an effect if they are added in abundance to food. Tinctures and syrups can be prepared as explained above.# Categorias:10,25,27,52,64#</item>
        <item> Nombre Científico:Aloe vera (L.) Burm . F.# Nombre Común:Aloe vera# Órgano o parte de la planta usada:Fresh leaves or the juice of the plant. The aloe leaf contains 95-96% water, but the other 4-5% contains no less than 70 substances with proven healing power, including amino acids, vitamins, minerals and enzymes.# Usos más comunes:Healing, anti-hemorrhoidal, anti-asthmatic and anti-cold; It is a protector of the liver, stimulator of the immune system, including T4 cells, which are the body‘s natural guardians against viruses and bacteria, which give it antiviral and antibacterial properties. Helps heal intestinal disorders, including diarrhea, constipation, ulcers, and colitis. A gel is obtained that can be used as a mild anesthetic. Reduces inflammation from arthritis. Reduces bad cholesterol and triglycerides. Protects the skin from radiation if applied topically. Reduces the symptoms of psoriasis. Accelerates wound healing. Relieves the effect of burns. It dilates the capillaries, strengthens circulation. It constitutes a natural colon cleanser, general invigorating, strong antioxidant.# Modo de uso y preparación:Aqueous extracts of the mesophyll of its leaves are prepared, as well as 25 and 50% creams, syrups, rectal ointment, vaginal suppository and subcutaneous or intramuscular injection. For cysts in the liver, take aloe, which alternates one year with the anamu plant and the other with aloe, peeled and diced.# Categorias:10,12,19,34,42,53,82,94# </item>
        <item>Nombre Científico:Anethum graveolens L.# Nombre Común:Dill# Órgano o parte de la planta usada:Ripe fruit and seeds.# Usos más comunes:Digestive, carminative, antispasmodic, diuretic, Vulnerary; for colic, especially in children. Its stimulating properties for milk production in nursing mothers have been proven. Also its seeds can fight bad breath.# Modo de uso y preparación:Its seeds are prepared in infusion, or in the form of tincture, although its seeds, chewed directly, are used to combat bad breath.# Categorias:16,40,46,54,57,98#</item>
        <item>Nombre Científico:Bixa orellana L.# Nombre Común:Achiote# Órgano o parte de la planta usada:The fresh fruit.# Usos más comunes:Against burns, astringent, febrifuge and antidote to poisoning by sour cassava. Diuretic properties are also known. The pulp of the fruits is useful for burns and as an insect repellent; the leaves are used as a poultice for headaches and as a decoction for oral conditions; its most common use is for dermatological conditions.# Modo de uso y preparación:The fluid extract of the dried and ground fruits is used for dermatological affections; Poultices and decoctions can be prepared with the leaves and pulp for burns and as a repellent.# Categorias:5,35,41,50,57,66,82#</item>
        <item>Nombre Científico:Capsicum annuum L.# Nombre Común:Common chili pepper, Pepper# Órgano o parte de la planta usada:Fruit.# Usos más comunes:Dermatological and antirheumatic. It is also anti-inflammatory, especially for the joints, and can combat neuralgia; Stimulating gastric and correct movement of the intestines, circulation; it is choleretic and vasodilator.# Modo de uso y preparación:The fruits eaten raw, or in food are used. For external use, 1% tinctures are prepared.# Categorias:21,26,44,50#</item>
        <item>Nombre Científico:Calendula officinalis L.# Nombre Común:Marigold# Órgano o parte de la planta usada:flowers.# Usos más comunes:Anti-inflammatory, choleretic, antiseptic, antiulcer (especially for gastric ulcers), healing, emenogogue, purifying. Topical use against conjunctivitis and ophthalmia, with eye irritation.# Modo de uso y preparación:It is prepared in fluid extracts and tinctures.# Categorias:21,27,31,42,44,48,79#</item>
        <item> Nombre Científico:Cassia alata L.# Nombre Común:Christmas candles,Candle bush# Órgano o parte de la planta usada:Leaves and seeds.# Usos más comunes:Dermatological, antifungal; It is used in America to combat ringworm, fungal conditions of the athlete‘s foot disease and to combat intestinal parasites. It has a proven laxative action.# Modo de uso y preparación:Decoctions are prepared with its leaves for skin conditions and its seeds for intestinal parasites.# Categorias:2,17,50,73# </item>
        <item>Nombre Científico:Cassia fistula L.# Nombre Común:Golden shower, Purging cassia# Órgano o parte de la planta usada:Pulp of the fruits, leaves, bark and roots.# Usos más comunes:Digestive, mild laxative. High content of minerals in its fruits, which is why they are used as an antianemic. In folk medicine, it is used for burns, and for malaria, arthritis, and respiratory conditions.# Modo de uso y preparación:It is prepared in decoctions in the case of roots and foliage; the pulp of the fruit can be ingested directly, diluted directly in boiling water, or dried and ground to prepare infusions.# Categorias:4,9,34,54,73,82#</item>
        <item>Nombre Científico:Cassia grandis L. f.# Nombre Común:Pink shower tree; Carao# Órgano o parte de la planta usada:Foliage, roots and fruit.# Usos más comunes:Antifungal, general antiseptic; antianemic, purgative.# Modo de uso y preparación:The juice of the leaves and roots has antiseptic properties, and in some countries of America it is used against syphilis. The pulp of the fruits has purgative properties, but it is also used to prepare soft drinks, macerated in water, or consumed directly for its antianemic properties.# Categorias:9,23,27#</item>
        <item>Nombre Científico:Cucurbita moschata# Nombre Común:Pumpkin# Órgano o parte de la planta usada:Seeds, leaves and pulp of the fruit.# Usos más comunes:Digestive, anthelmintic; antidiarrheal (leaves); laxative (seeds); fights benign inflammation of the prostate and urinary infections; It is also an emollient (treatment of pimples, freckles, etc.) and to treat burns.# Modo de uso y preparación:The seeds are crushed and ingested with honey or sugar in the case of their purgative action; the pulp of the boiled fruit acts against slow digestions; the decoctions of the leaves are used to lower fever and as an antidiarrheal.# Categorias:18,24,25,54,61,73,82#</item>
        <item>Nombre Científico:Cymbopogom citratus# Nombre Común:Lemon grass# Órgano o parte de la planta usada:The entire leaf area.# Usos más comunes:Antispasmodic; for stomach and respiratory conditions (asthma); analgesic, anticatarrhal, diuretic and hypotensive. Antimicrobial properties have also been demonstrated.# Modo de uso y preparación:The decoctions and fluid extracts are used in various concentrations. Decoctions should be filtered through a fine cloth to remove silica crystals, which are considered carcinogenic.# Categorias:4,6,10,12,16,57,71#</item>
        <item>Nombre Científico:Eucalyptus citriodora Hook.# Nombre Común:Lemon Eucalyptus# Órgano o parte de la planta usada:Sheets.# Usos más comunes:Antiseptic, anti-inflammatory, antitussive, respiratory, dermatological, expectorant, antiasthmatic and astringent. It is also used in bronchitis, laryngitis and sinusitis; it is antipyretic and antirheumatic.# Modo de uso y preparación:The leaves are used in infusions for vaporization; in general, fluid extracts are used.# Categorias:10,21,25,26,27,30,35,50,64,86#</item>
        <item>Nombre Científico:Foeniculum vulgare Mill .# Nombre Común:Fennel# Órgano o parte de la planta usada:leaf.# Usos más comunes:Carminative, diuretic, against hiccups, hypotensive, for digestive conditions, antispasmodic, antiseptic and stimulant. It is also used as a reliever in case of bronchitis and cough. It stimulates the secretion of milk in nursing mothers and against vomiting.# Modo de uso y preparación:The most used is the infusion of the dried seeds or the fluid extracts and the tincture. The rest of the parts in the same way.# Categorias:16,27,40,57,62,71#</item>
        <item>Nombre Científico:Hibiscus sabdariffa L.# Nombre Común:Jamaica flower# Órgano o parte de la planta usada:Flowers, leaves and roots.# Usos más comunes:Antipyretic, stimulates intestinal activity, hypotensive, reduces blood viscosity, antispasmodic and antibacterial, reduces alcoholic intoxication, relieves cough and in the form of lavatories, it is used to disinfect wounds. It also has stomatic and emollient properties. The infused calyces give an excellent red-colored refreshment. In Brazil they esteem the bitter roots.# Modo de uso y preparación:In infusions of calyces or leaves, or in root decoctions, depending on the condition.# Categorias:11,16,25,61,71#</item>
        <item>Nombre Científico:Jasminum officinale L.# Nombre Común:Common jasmine, Jasmine# Órgano o parte de la planta usada:Flower# Usos más comunes:Sedative and they also use it for the heart.# Modo de uso y preparación:Infusiones de las flores.# Categorias:88#</item>
        <item>Nombre Científico:Justicia pectoralis Jacq .# Nombre Común:Linden# Órgano o parte de la planta usada:Leaves and branches.# Usos más comunes:Sedative, pectoral and antispasmodic.# Modo de uso y preparación:In infusions or in decoctions of the foliage.# Categorias:16,81,88#</item>
        <item>Nombre Científico:Matricaria recutita L.# Nombre Común:Chamomile# Órgano o parte de la planta usada:Flowers, leaves and the aerial part in general.# Usos más comunes:Skin and digestive conditions; it is antidiarrheal, anti-inflammatory, antispasmodic, skin softening, antifungal, antiviral, antibacterial; it can be used for psoriasis and lymphangitis, for acute diarrhea and dysmenorrhea. It is sedative and vasodilator, as well as being used as a healing agent.# Modo de uso y preparación:It is prepared in creams for dermatological use, although in that case fluid extracts can also be used. Its best known use is prepared as an infusion.# Categorias:2,11,14,16,17,21,32,42,53,56,88#</item>
        <item>Nombre Científico:Mentha arvensis L.# Nombre Común:Japanese Mint# Órgano o parte de la planta usada:Sheets.# Usos más comunes:Antiseptic, anti-inflammatory, antispasmodic, carminative and antihistamine.# Modo de uso y preparación:In infusions or decoctions, syrups, tinctures, inhalations, ointments, nasal drops and liniments. The essential oil in its leaves is a strong antihistamine.# Categorias:16,21,27,40#</item>
        <item>Nombre Científico:Mentha spicata Willd .# Nombre Común:Spearmint, Garden mint, Common mint# Órgano o parte de la planta usada:Foliage.# Usos más comunes:Antiseptic, anti-inflammatory of the respiratory system, antispasmodic and carminative.# Modo de uso y preparación:Foliage infusions, fluid extracts and tinctures.# Categorias:16,21,27,40#</item>
        <item> Nombre Científico:Morinda citrifolia L.# Nombre Común:Noni# Órgano o parte de la planta usada:Fruit and leaves.# Usos más comunes:Cleansing, emmenagogue and nutritional supplement. It acts as an accelerator in the cure of countless diseases, such as diabetes, cancer, arthritis, asthma, digestive problems and others.# Modo de uso y preparación:The leaves heated by fire or withered relieve pain in swelling and as a poultice on wounds. Consumption as a nutritional supplement in the form of juice increases the presence of T cells, which release chemical substances that attract phagocytes that discover the presence of pathogens and absorb them. It contains active substances called Proxeronines, which the body converts into Xeronines.# Categorias:10,34,51,59,52# </item>
        <item>Nombre Científico:Nasturtium oficinalis R.B.# Nombre Común:Watercress# Órgano o parte de la planta usada:Foliage.# Usos más comunes:Pectoral, respiratory diseases, antiscorbutics, tonic, purifying and cholagogue. It is also used against diabetes, goiter and anemia. It restores the intestinal flora acting on candidiasis in the intestine.# Modo de uso y preparación:The plant is chopped, and infusions are made. The decoction of fresh leaves is recommended to take as common water for stomach aches. The infusion of its branches is used for diabetes, goiter and anemia. Crushed and crushed, use the extract, with a frequency of 2 to 3 tablespoons daily.# Categorias:4,15,43,49,52,81,92#</item>
        <item>Nombre Científico:Ocimum basilicum L.# Nombre Común:Great basil# Órgano o parte de la planta usada:Foliage.# Usos más comunes:Antispasmodic, carminative and digestive; It is also used against diseases of the respiratory tract, for headaches, to lower fever, in the form of friction. It is proven antimicrobial and antispasmodic.# Modo de uso y preparación:Fluid extracts are generally used.# Categorias:4,16,24,25,40,41,54#</item>
        <item>Nombre Científico:Ocimum gratissimum L.# Nombre Común:Clove basil, African basil# Órgano o parte de la planta usada:Leaves.# Usos más comunes:Antispasmodic, expectorant and antitussive. Anti-flu and fever-reducing properties are attributed to it. It has proven antispasmodic action.# Modo de uso y preparación:In decoctions of the leaves and in fluid extracts.# Categorias:16,30,64#</item>
        <item>Nombre Científico:Ocimum sanctum L.# Nombre Común:Holy basil # Órgano o parte de la planta usada:Foliage.# Usos más comunes:Antispasmodic, against diabetes mellitus. It is also proven antimicrobial and antidepressant.# Modo de uso y preparación:70% fluid extracts are used, and oily extracts are also used in dental medicine.# Categorias:16,24,52#</item>
        <item>Nombre Científico:Origanum majorana L.# Nombre Común:Marjoram# Órgano o parte de la planta usada:Foliage.# Usos más comunes:Carminative, antidiarrheal, antispasmodic and anticatarrhal. It is also tonic and sedative.# Modo de uso y preparación:In infusions or decoctions, depending on the part of the foliage in question.# Categorias:12,14,16,40,88,92#</item>
        <item>Nombre Científico:Orthosiphon aristatus# Nombre Común:Cat‘s whiskers, Java tea# Órgano o parte de la planta usada:Sheets# Usos más comunes:Tonic, antispasmodic, carminative, diuretic, antitussive and litholytic. It has certain properties against diabetes. It acts on arteriosclerosis and hypertension.# Modo de uso y preparación:It is used in infusions and decoctions.# Categorias:16,30,40,52,57,75,92#</item>
        <item>Nombre Científico:Piper auritum Kunt h.# Nombre Común:Sacred pepper, Vera Cruz pepper# Órgano o parte de la planta usada:Sheets# Usos más comunes:Emollient, diuretic, antirheumatic, stimulant, antispasmodic and anti-inflammatory. The extract has proven antispasmodic action, as well as analgesic and anti-inflammatory; in alcoholic extract it has antibacterial properties.# Modo de uso y preparación:The leaves are used directly applied to the inflamed part, or the 70% fluid extracts against pain. The alcoholic extract against bacterial and fungal infections.# Categorias:6,11,16,21,26,57,61,62,#</item>
        <item>Nombre Científico:Plantago lanceolata L.# Nombre Común:Ribwort plantain, Narrowleaf plantain, English plantain# Órgano o parte de la planta usada:The aerial part.# Usos más comunes:Liver and kidney diseases, angina; anticatarrhal, anti-inflammatory; against renal colic, ulcers, stomach ulcers, burns, stomatitis; It is antitussive and mild expectorant; astringent in diarrhea.# Modo de uso y preparación:The decoction is used orally for inflammations of the digestive tract, or of the gums; it is also used for compresses in skin and eye conditions; You can also prepare skin creams.# Categorias:2,7,12,21,30,35,45,63,64,70,82,83,94#</item>
        <item>Nombre Científico:Plantago major L.# Nombre Común:Plantago major; Broadleaf plantain# Órgano o parte de la planta usada:Aerial part.# Usos más comunes:Liver and kidney diseases, angina; anticatarrhal, anti-inflammatory; against renal colic, ulcers, stomach ulcers, burns, stomatitis; It is antitussive and mild expectorant; astringent in diarrhea.# Modo de uso y preparación:The decoction is used orally for inflammations of the digestive tract, or of the gums; it is also used for compresses in skin and eye conditions; You can also prepare skin creams.# Categorias:2,7,12,21,30,45,53,63,64,70,82,83,94#</item>
        <item>Nombre Científico:Protium cubense Urb .# Nombre Común:Copal# Órgano o parte de la planta usada:Foliage and resin.# Usos más comunes:The decoction of the aerial part is anticatarrhal and antiasthmatic. The resin is useful in the extraction of thorns. It is used for headaches and neck pain.# Modo de uso y preparación:The decoctions of the foliage and extraction of the resin for friction, with direct application in sore places.# Categorias:10,12,26,41#</item>
        <item>Nombre Científico:Psidium guajava L.# Nombre Común:Guava# Órgano o parte de la planta usada:Sheets.# Usos más comunes:Digestive, antidiarrheal and bactericidal against staphylococci.# Modo de uso y preparación: It is frequently used in gastrointestinal diseases such as diarrhea, chills and stomach pain, by infusing the leaves three times a day or as long-term water.# Categorias:14,36,54#</item>
        <item>Nombre Científico:Rhizophora Mangle L.# Nombre Común:Red Mangrove# Órgano o parte de la planta usada:The crust.# Usos más comunes:Astringent, against hepatitis and antidiarrheal; It is used as a healing agent for skin ulcers. Maceration in water purifies the blood, is anti-haemorrhagic and febrifugal.# Modo de uso y preparación:The crushed bark with water is used, and after a rest, the liquid is decanted that can be concentrated and prepared as a tincture or in gels, which are applied to the wounds or used orally. Decoctions of the bark are also prepared.# Categorias:2,14,35,42,66,94#</item>
        <item>Nombre Científico:Rosmarinus Officinalis L.# Nombre Común:Rosemary# Órgano o parte de la planta usada:Foliage.# Usos más comunes:Choleretic and protector of liver tissue, antispasmodic; carminative and antiseptic; for circulation and nerves, in colds, bronchitis and asthma; for muscle aches, rheumatism and sciatica; it also has analgesic properties.# Modo de uso y preparación:The infusion of dried leaves is recommended for dyspepsia, vomiting and vertigo. Alcoholic maceration is useful for rheumatism, muscle aches and sciatica; Tinctures and elixirs are also made and the oil from its leaves is used for friction.# Categorias:6,10,12,16,27,40,44,70,87#</item>
        <item>Nombre Científico:Ruta Graveolens L.# Nombre Común:Rue# Órgano o parte de la planta usada:Leaves.# Usos más comunes:Abortive, emmenagogue, for earaches, anthelmintic and sedative. Soothes headaches, hysteria, tachycardia and other symptoms of anxiety, as well as mild disorders of the digestive system; it also increases peripheral circulation, strengthens the capillary wall and lowers blood pressure.# Modo de uso y preparación:The infusion of the dried leaves is used as a sedative, for dyspepsia, headache, hysteria and other symptoms of anxiety; but its most frequent use is extracting the juice from its leaves for earache.# Categorias:1,18,41,59,88#</item>
        <item>Nombre Científico:Salvia Officinalis L.# Nombre Común:Sage, Garden sage# Órgano o parte de la planta usada:Sheets# Usos más comunes:Antinfectious in general; antifungal in particular, anti-inflammatory; urinary antiseptic, bronchodilator and expectorant. It also has carminative properties; It is used for conditions of the pharynx, larynx and tonsils.# Modo de uso y preparación:It is prepared in syrups, but also in mouthwashes against the affections of the respiratory system; sage preparations must be filtered like those of holy cane, due to the presence of silica crystals.# Categorias:17,20,21,27,37,40,64#</item>
        <item>Nombre Científico:Zingiber Officinale Roscoe.# Nombre Común:Ginger# Órgano o parte de la planta usada:Rhizomes.# Usos más comunes:Antispasmodic, anticoleric, carminative, antitussive, anthelmintic and tonic. It is also used in irritable bowel disease. As for the respiratory system, it is antipyretic, sinusitis decongestant. In the circulatory system, it dissolves clots, lowers blood cholesterol levels and improves circulation in the lower limbs. It also relieves pain, applied externally, for toothaches and arthritis.# Modo de uso y preparación:It is used as a condiment in innumerable international dishes, thus it can also be prepared as an infusion and consumed as tea or as compresses; it can be ingested directly without any problem. It is contraindicated in pregnancy and lactation, kidney problems, as it is excreted through the kidney, as well as in the case of the use of anticoagulant drugs. It must be used with caution, as it tends to increase the pressure.# Categorias:13,16,18,25,30,34,40,86,92#</item>
        <item>Nombre Científico:Annona montana# Nombre Común:Soursop# Órgano o parte de la planta usada:leaves, stems, flowers, fruits and seeds.# Usos más comunes:The leaves are used as hypotensive, for the pain of pneumonia, cough, catarrh and poultice in inflammations. The juice of the fruit for hematuria, symptoms of burning when urinating, induce sweating, in digestive disorders and as an antidiarrheal.# Modo de uso y preparación:Six shoots are cut from the plant and crushed, put in two liters of water and placed in the sun for two hours, a quarter cup is supplied three times a day. The rest is applied in the form of baths in children and in adults, the head and thorax. The decoction administered orally for diarrhea and flu. The seeds crushed into liquor for lice. Eight petals are prepared in two cups of water, boiled for 15 min, and half a cup is administered three times a day for cases of cough and fever.# Categorias:12,14,30,54,71#</item>
        <item>Nombre Científico:Argemone mexicana.# Nombre Común:Mexican poppy, Cardosanto# Órgano o parte de la planta usada:leaves and roots.# Usos más comunes:In recurrent fever, of long evolution and difficult to lower, as it stimulates sweating. In cooking for kidney stones, the juice of the crushed leaves heated over the fire is strained through a fine cloth. The decoction of the root for the treatment of cancer, as well as to stimulate the production and elimination of urine in patients with fluid retention, in some cases can have an emetic effect, which is successful as one of the therapeutic actions and to stimulate menstruation. .# Modo de uso y preparación:The juice extracted from the previously heated leaves is applied topically in the treatment of wounds and then the affected area is covered with a bandage. The cooking of a quarter cup of leaves with a tablespoon of chamomile and a lemon or sour orange peel cut into small pieces is simmered in a liter of water for 15 min, a cup of hot water is administered very hot. 250 mL three times a day, while the fever persists or for the treatment of kidney stones.# Categorias:25,59,60#</item>
        <item>Nombre Científico:Bromelia pingüin L.# Nombre Común:Bromelia pinguin# Órgano o parte de la planta usada:fruit.# Usos más comunes:Fruit juice for parasites, roasted fruit for worms. An antirheumatic syrup is prepared with the juice of the roasted fruit, water and two parts of sugar.# Modo de uso y preparación:Three or four fruits are prepared, cut into small pieces, placed in half a liter of water with six tablespoons of sugar, boiled for 30 min, half a cup is administered every six hours until symptoms improve, after cooling the remedy. Two or three fruits are prepared, peeled mixed with sugar, put in the serene three nights in a row, covered with a fine cloth, after that time a tablespoon is administered on an empty stomach for three days, it is repeated two days from the seventh, in this way It is indicated in the treatment of giardiasis and oxyuriasis.# Categorias:26#</item>
        <item>Nombre Científico:Artemisia absinthium# Nombre Común:Wormwood, Absinthe, Wormit# Órgano o parte de la planta usada:Leaves, branches and flowers.# Usos más comunes:Taken on an empty stomach for the treatment of lobrices, the branches with leaves and flowers in cooking as a stimulant of the body, colicky stomach pains, diarrhea, dysentery and in the treatment of inflammatory diseases of the bones, including rheumatic crises due to elevated uric acid. The branches with flowers macerated and put in rum to treat joint pain, accompanied by cramps, applying it in the form of friction or poultice on the affected area. In digestive disorders accompanied by vomiting, flatulence and diarrhea of various causes, including dysentery. In menstrual disorders, as a stimulant, to lower fever and prevent hair loss.# Modo de uso y preparación:A decoction is prepared with a quarter cup of the flowering branches in two cups of water, letting it boil for 30 min over a low heat, half a cup is administered on an empty stomach and a half at bedtime for seven days. For hair loss, the same decoction is applied three times a week for 30 min, subsequently rinsing with plenty of water. To strengthen the stomach and improve digestion, it is mixed with honey to make a syrup, of which a tablespoon is taken after each meal.# Categorias:25,26,46,53,54,55,87,92#</item>
        <item>Nombre Científico:Bidens pilosa# Nombre Común:Black-jack, Beggarticks, Cobblers pegs# Órgano o parte de la planta usada:The leaves, stems, flowers, seeds and roots.# Usos más comunes:The leaves of the stems are crushed to heal skin ulcerations and dog bites. The flowers in decoction for ulcerative colitis and enemas in dysentery with irritation of the intestines. The root decoction for respiratory conditions such as influenza and asthma. The decoction of two to three branches in half a liter of water and a pinch of salt to apply as nasal drops in cases of nasal catarrh and sinusitis. In canker sores, tonsillitis and pharyngitis, the cooking of the seeds in hepatitis.# Modo de uso y preparación:Prepare half a cup of fresh flowers to a liter of water and once strained it is applied in enemas for colitis, dysentery and relief of intestinal inflammation. The decoction of the flowers by mouth for heartburn and digestive disorders. Half a cup of roots of the plant cut into small pieces is prepared for three cups of water, simmered for 30 min and administered three cups a day. for colds with a runny nose and sinusitis, one dropper is applied to each nostril three times a day, in children a quarter dropper is recommended three times a day for a week.# Categorias:11,17,26,31,55,94#</item>
        <item>Nombre Científico:Parthenium hysterophorus L.# Nombre Común:Santa-Maria, Whitetop weed# Órgano o parte de la planta usada:The roots, the flowers and the whole plant.# Usos más comunes:It is used as a home remedy against fever and in baths, for pimples. It works well as a febrifuge and against cranial neuralgia. It is also considered a gastric hypostenizer, a stomach tonic and stimulant. This plant is bitter, febrifuge, juice useful topically against tuberculous and syphilitic ulcers.# Modo de uso y preparación:Against malarial fevers, the root of the bitter broom is prepared in the following manner, the root is macerated and boiled in water until it is reduced to one third. This decoction is taken on an empty stomach and at bedtime, two tablespoons each time. This is repeated for several days. The decoction or the powder of the whole plant, applied in an ointment, gives positive results against herpes, scabies and ringworm. Other people use it in baths against pimples, and cooking for the heart. The infusion is purifying and emmenagogue.# Categorias:28,66,92#</item>
        <item>Nombre Científico:Persea americana# Nombre Común:Avocado# Órgano o parte de la planta usada:Leaves.# Usos más comunes:Cholesterol and diabetes. To face severe pain caused by osteoarthritis, arthritis, bursitis and rheumatic pain in general.# Modo de uso y preparación:For cholesterol, boil seven leaves in a liter of water and drink as long as water. For rheumatic pain, prepare a decoction or decoction with 15 or 20 avocado leaves (green or purple). These leaves are poured into a container that contains one liter of water. It is brought to a simmer for 8 to 10 minutes. After that, it is strained with gauze or antiseptic cloth and packaged in a glass bottle, preferably an amber one. It is stored in the cold and at least three glasses are taken a day morning, noon and night.# Categorias:52,87#</item>
        <item>Nombre Científico:Bougainvillea glabra# Nombre Común:Lesser bougainvillea, Paperflower# Órgano o parte de la planta usada:The Flower.# Usos más comunes:Reduces dry cough Expectorant, helps eliminate mucus lodged in the upper respiratory tract (larynx, pharynx, bronchi). Antipyretic (reduces fever).# Modo de uso y preparación:Boil some flowers in a liter of water. Drink as long as water while coughing occurs.# Categorias:30,64#</item>
        <item> Nombre Científico:Petiveria alliacea# Nombre Común:Guinea henweed, Anamu# Órgano o parte de la planta usada:root.# Usos más comunes:For cysts in the liver, colic, flu and for pimples commonly called born.# Modo de uso y preparación:For flu, crush two roots in two cans of vaporub and inhale for two days. Make a decoction of anamu and drink for a year as ordinary water. In a container pour two cucumbers of water with leaves, stem and roots that is boiled for 10 minutes.# Categorias:46# </item>
        <item>Nombre Científico:Crescentia cujete# Nombre Común:Calabash tree# Órgano o parte de la planta usada:Fruits and seeds.# Usos más comunes:The decoction fruit is taken orally to treat diarrhea, stomach pain, colds, bronchitis, cough, asthma, and urethritis. The leaves are used to treat hypertension.# Modo de uso y preparación:For asthma, prepare a tea with scorpion root and drink# Categorias:30,53#</item>
        <item>Nombre Científico:Rhoeo discolor# Nombre Común:Boatlily, Moses-in-the-cradle,# Órgano o parte de la planta usada:The sheet.# Usos más comunes:Cardiocirculatory. It is used in the treatment of headaches, sprains and trauma and as a regulator of blood pressure. Vaginal infection.# Modo de uso y preparación:Boil a leaf in enough water to use in sitz baths. Against the headache, the leaves are applied to the head (passed through the fire), smeared with vaporub, and tied with a cloth.# Categorias:39#</item>
        <item>Nombre Científico:Mangifera indica# Nombre Común:Mango# Órgano o parte de la planta usada:leaf.# Usos más comunes:The decoction of the roots is taken as a diuretic and for the treatment of gastrointestinal diseases, this decoction is also used to prepare tinctures to treat vitiligo. Chewing the leaves strengthens the teeth and against mouth blisters for this the direct application of the tree‘s resin is also used. The infusion of the bark is used in the treatment of malaria and rinses on the hair with this decoction help to darken the hair and prevent it from falling out.# Modo de uso y preparación:Prepare a leaf tea and make mouthwashes.# Categorias:#</item>
        <item>Nombre Científico:Azadirachta indica# Nombre Común:Nimtree, Neem, Indian lilac# Órgano o parte de la planta usada:Leaf.# Usos más comunes:Psoriasis, diabetes, AIDS, cancer, herpes, dental disorders, dermatology, allergies, ulcers, hepatitis, fungi, external parasites. Heart conditions.# Modo de uso y preparación: For diabetes, boil 10 leaves in two liters of water and drink as long as water. It controls cardiac arrhythmias and also delays blood clotting. It is effective against acne, rash, dandruff. Inhibits allergic reactions when applied externally. Neem extract accelerates the healing of gastric lesions. The oil of the seeds and the extract of the Neem leaves are used, it reduces itching and pain.# Categorias:39,50,52,38,94#</item>
        <item>Nombre Científico:Mimosa pudica# Nombre Común:Sensitive plant, Sleepy plant# Órgano o parte de la planta usada:The branches.# Usos más comunes:Kidney.# Modo de uso y preparación:Boil the branches in water and drink as long as water.# Categorias:83#</item>
        <item>Nombre Científico:Cissus sicyoides L.# Nombre Común:Princess vine, Seasonvine# Órgano o parte de la planta usada:The leaves, branches and fruit# Usos más comunes:This species is attributed anti-inflammatory, anti-rheumatic properties, against abscesses.# Modo de uso y preparación:The leaves are used as an anti-flu, anti-inflammatory, diuretic and facilitator of childbirth. The leaves are sometimes applied to pimples or inflammations and the decoction of the stems is used as a remedy for rheumatism. The decoction of equal parts of stems and leaves is a positive remedy against the flu, if it is drunk at the rate of four cups a day, as hot as possible, as a sudorific. This same application gives good results against rheumatism. Ripe grapes are slightly laxative and raisins are used as pectorals in cooking and infusion. It is a good remedy for hemorrhoids, the ground plant is used in a poultice to combat inflammation.# Categorias:21,26,32#</item>
        <item>Nombre Científico:Momordica charantia L.# Nombre Común:Bitter melon, Bitter apple# Órgano o parte de la planta usada:Fruit, seeds# Usos más comunes:The immature fruits may have some antibiotics, anticancer, antiviral and other properties especially suitable for use in the treatment of malaria, HIV and diabetes.# Modo de uso y preparación:The tea is prepared with some dried slices of cundeamor or with its dried leaves, leaving it in boiling water for 10 minutes.# Categorias:24,52#</item>
        <item>Nombre Científico:Lavandula angustifolia# Nombre Común:Lavender# Órgano o parte de la planta usada:Its flowers, leaves and stem# Usos más comunes:Analgesic, cell regenerator, sedative, helps to reduce the symptoms of flu and colds ... always using the essential oil that is extracted from the plant. But above all it has great antiseptic power.# Modo de uso y preparación:Dip several dried lavender flowers in boiling water, let it steep for about 10 minutes, strain, and serve. You can consume it both hot and cold.# Categorias:6,12,27#</item>
        <item>Nombre Científico:Passiflora incarnata# Nombre Común:Maypop, Purple passionflower# Órgano o parte de la planta usada:Flower, foliage# Usos más comunes:Sedative, Antispasmodic. It is used to combat insomnia.# Modo de uso y preparación:Fluid extract or as a herbal medicine# Categorias:88,16#</item>
        <item>Nombre Científico:Valeriana officinalis# Nombre Común:Valerian# Órgano o parte de la planta usada:The underground organs are used (rhizomes, roots and stolons)# Usos más comunes:It is used to treat insomnia, nervous anxiety and to help relax people who suffer from pain in the body.# Modo de uso y preparación:Bring a cup of water to a boil and leave it until it reaches a boiling point. When done, add the valerian root and cover. Let it sit for 10 minutes and strain it.# Categorias:88#</item>
        <item>Nombre Científico:Senna tora (L.) # Nombre Común:Sickle senna# Órgano o parte de la planta usada:The seeds, the leaves and the root.# Usos más comunes:Spasmodic, skin rashes, fever, ulcers and skin eruptions.# Modo de uso y preparación:The roasted seeds like coffee are used in the field, mainly in Las Villas, as a decoction, in spasmodic pains; and the root in skin eruptions, in bathrooms; the cooking of the leaf or the root against fever. The leaves are given as a decoction as an aperitif to children who suffer from fevers during dentition. Fried in palm oil, they are applied to ulcers; The ground seeds and mixed with butter are used to mitigate the itchiness of herpetic eruptions. The root, rubbed with lemon juice, is a good remedy for rashes and insteps.# Categorias:#</item>
        <item>Nombre Científico:Lancewood # Nombre Común:Yaya# Órgano o parte de la planta usada:Peel and between peel.# Usos más comunes:Anticoagulant, anti-inflammatory, antiseptic and antispasmodic.# Modo de uso y preparación:Cocimiento. The entre peel is taken and boiled for 5 minutes, swish or applied in fomentations. You can drink it. Swish 3 times a day, drink it if necessary 2 or 3 times a day a cup of coffee.# Categorias:16,21,27#</item>
        <item>Nombre Científico:Plectranthus amboinicu# Nombre Común:Indian borage, Indian mint, Cuban oregano# Órgano o parte de la planta usada:Leaves.# Usos más comunes:Anticonvulsant, antiepileptic, antiasthmatic, antiphlogistic, antispasmodic, anti-inflammatory, sedative, bronchodilator and antimicrobial.# Modo de uso y preparación:As a decoction for the treatment of bronchial colds, it calms coughs, relieves stomach pain and facilitates heavy digestions. Cooking a bunch of leaves for a bottle of water after meals to relieve stomach aches and poor digestion. # Categorias:10,16,21,24,37#</item>
        <item>Nombre Científico:Catharanthus roseus# Nombre Común:Bright eyes, Cape periwinkle# Órgano o parte de la planta usada:The petals# Usos más comunes:The decoction of its petals is used for diseases of the eyes, conjunctivitis, meatiness and to strengthen eyesight. Antibiotic properties are attributed to it both in internal infections and in the skin, to lower blood pressure, cholesterol and cure malaria. It is also useful in cases of laryngitis, pharyngitis and toothache.# Modo de uso y preparación:For conjunctivitis, pour half a liter of water with 3 Vicarious Flowers into a container for a period of 2 or 3 hours and then apply compresses 3 times a day.# Categorias:49#</item>
        <item>Nombre Científico:Phyllanthus niruri# Nombre Común:Gale of the wind, Stonebreaker# Órgano o parte de la planta usada:The flower, the root and the seeds# Usos más comunes:Studies suggest that it provides a series of health benefits such as fighting kidney stones and protecting the liver, because it has diuretic and hepatoprotective properties, it is also antioxidant, cholagogue, antiviral, antibacterial, antispasmodic and hypoglycemic.# Modo de uso y preparación:With 20 g of chancapiedra; 1L of water, boil the water and add the medicinal plant, let it rest for 5 to 10 minutes, strain and drink warm, preferably without adding sugar. Take 1 to 2 cups a day.# Categorias:11,16,32,43,57#</item>
        <item>Nombre Científico:Stachytarpheta jamaicensis# Nombre Común:Blue porterweed, Jamaica vervain# Órgano o parte de la planta usada:Leaves# Usos más comunes:This species is used mainly in the treatment of discomfort or pain associated with the digestive system. It is used topically to treat skin diseases or infections (bacterial infections, pimples). It can relieve toothaches caused by cavities or nerve exposure. It has diuretic properties and benefits the menstrual cycle of women.# Modo de uso y preparación:For all the properties mentioned above, the leaves are used in topical preparations or infusions.# Categorias:57#</item>
        <item>Nombre Científico:Portulaca oleracea# Nombre Común:Duckweed, Little hogweed, Pursley# Órgano o parte de la planta usada:Stems, leaves and flowers# Usos más comunes:It helps to improve circulation and cardiovascular function. It is diuretic, promotes excretion, has anti-inflammatory properties, has been used as an analgesic, antiseptic and antifungal, beneficial for diabetes, helps against anemia.# Modo de uso y preparación:It can be eaten fresh as a salad, or cooked as spinach# Categorias:6,17,21,27,52,57#</item>
        <item>Nombre Científico:Boldoa purpurascens# Nombre Común:Nitro# Órgano o parte de la planta usada:Leaves# Usos más comunes:Recent studies showed that the extracts of this plant have high diuretic activity and for the treatment of kidney diseases with good results.# Modo de uso y preparación:Aqueous extracts and decoctions# Categorias:57#</item>
        <item>Nombre Científico:Citrus limon# Nombre Común:Lemon# Órgano o parte de la planta usada:Leaves and fruits# Usos más comunes:Lemons, due to their high content of vitamin C and flavonoids, help strengthen your immune system by increasing your body‘s defenses. They also prevent diseases, especially of the respiratory tract.# Modo de uso y preparación:In lemonade and the leaves are prepared in cooking# Categorias:#</item>
        <item>Nombre Científico:Cocos nucifera# Nombre Común:Coconut# Órgano o parte de la planta usada:The fruit.# Usos más comunes:Anemia, stomach pain, kidney and among its various medicinal properties of coconut water helps regulate blood pressure and blood sugar and cholesterol levels. It also helps to deworm.# Modo de uso y preparación:For anemia, boil a liter of water and place a chopped sweet potato, drink as long as water. For stomach pain, boil or crush some leaves and spread on the stomach, the liquid that is found naturally inside the coconut. To deworm, prepare a coconut water smoothie, with a few leaves of apasote and pumpkin seeds. This is taken for three days on an empty stomach.# Categorias:#</item>
        <item>Nombre Científico:Iatropha aethiopica Muell.# Nombre Común:Chaya# Órgano o parte de la planta usada:Leaves, stems and roots# Usos más comunes:Many of the scholars assure that its consumption increases the retention of calcium, thus enriching bone mass, mainly in children and adolescents, in whom, in addition, it contributes to the growth and development of the entire musculoskeletal system. Other specialists argue that it facilitates digestion, and fights constipation, helps to expel urine and breast milk. It is also associated with other medicinal and preventive properties such as the normalization of numerous body functions, prevents anemia, improves memory and brain functions, and fights arthritis and diabetes. It prevents coughing, while decongesting and disinfecting the lungs.# Modo de uso y preparación:Its most common consumption, for medicinal purposes is in the form of tea# Categorias:34,52#</item>
        <item>Nombre Científico:Chenopodium ambrosioides L.# Nombre Común:Jesuit‘s tea, Mexican-tea# Órgano o parte de la planta usada:Whole plant.# Usos más comunes: The essence of this plant is used as an effective folk remedy against intestinal parasites. Well known as an effective vermifuge and the juice of the leaves and stems is used in washes to cure hemorrhoids.# Modo de uso y preparación:Against giardiasis, a solution is made with a tablespoon of juice from the leaves and stems of Apasote, which is poured into a glass with 2 to 3 ounces of coconut milk. To carry out the treatment, a tablespoon of honey is taken on an empty stomach, after 15 minutes the aforementioned solution is ingested and nothing is eaten for an hour. The procedure is done for 3 days. It rests for a week and is repeated for another 3 days. For hemorrhoids, a decoction or decoction prepared with leaves and stems of Apasote is made.# Categorias:#</item>
        <item>Nombre Científico:Smilax aspera# Nombre Común:Common smilax, Sarsaparille# Órgano o parte de la planta usada:The roots# Usos más comunes:They are used especially in cases of rheumatism and skin diseases (eczema, psoriasis), also in cases of flu, anorexia or gout. It has diuretic and diaphoretic action, because it favors circulation.# Modo de uso y preparación:Infusion for the bladder and kidney. Boil it for 2 minutes, let it infuse for 10 more minutes, strain it and take two cups a day on an empty stomach.# Categorias:57,87#</item>
        <item>Nombre Científico:Urera baccifera (L) Gaud# Nombre Común:Chichicaste, Scratchbush# Órgano o parte de la planta usada:Leaves and flowers# Usos más comunes:It is anti-inflammatory, analgesic, diuretic, rubefacient, blistering, and in cases of fever, gonorrhea, malaria, arthritis and rheumatism; against rheumatic pain and a series of general illnesses under the name of allergies. The leaves are used and the affected part is rubbed with them.# Modo de uso y preparación:It is used in decoction of its leaves and flowers.# Categorias:6,21,34,57,87#</item>
        <item>Nombre Científico:Xanthium occidentales B.# Nombre Común:Rough cocklebur, Clotbur# Órgano o parte de la planta usada:Leaves# Usos más comunes:It is used in lotions and to contain bleeding and treat scrofula. Cooking of the roots for kidney and liver diseases and as an anticancer. The leaves remove the spots from the face, if you have stones# Modo de uso y preparación:Put them in a saucepan with a cup of water, cover and boil for ten minutes. After that time, turn off the heat and let it cool. Take a cup of this decoction three times a day for three days. Keep in mind that you must prepare it each time you go to ingest it.# Categorias:3,70#</item>
        <item>Nombre Científico:Hibiscus rosa-sinensis# Nombre Común:Chinese hibiscus, Hawaiian hibiscus# Órgano o parte de la planta usada:Flowers# Usos más comunes:Against cough and hoarseness, externally, applied by poultices made with the seeds boiled in milk, it serves to soothe the intense itching of the skin. Strengthens the immune system.# Modo de uso y preparación:A cup of water is boiled, two flowers are added and it is left to rest for five minutes after which the flowers are removed and the liquid is sweetened with a teaspoon of honey. The cooked flowers to which sugar and arabic gum are added is magnificent to combat coughs and hoarseness. To strengthen your immune system, it is recommended to prepare a kind of smoothie with 6 complete red Pacific Sea flowers. First, each of the petals must be washed well to remove impurities, then the flowers are placed in an 8-ounce glass, 3 tablespoons of honey are added, preferably, the honey of the earth. Subsequently, it is passed through the blender and after mixing it is strained with an antiseptic cloth. You cannot add sugar to this remedy. It is drunk after straining twice a day, in the morning and in the evening.# Categorias:#</item>
        <item>Nombre Científico:Commelina elegans# Nombre Común:White mouth dayflower, Widow‘s tears# Órgano o parte de la planta usada:Leaves# Usos más comunes:Diuretic, also as an emollient, softens or reduces tumors, and adds that the cooking of the leaves is very good for any intestinal inflammation, this cooking is also used as a purifying agent in venereal diseases, and in kidney and bladder conditions. # Modo de uso y preparación:After cooking with very little water and grinding, it is used as an emollient poultice. The highly concentrated decoction prepared with the whole plant is commonly used for fostering, lavatory, injections and baths, both local and general.# Categorias:57,61#</item>
        <item>Nombre Científico:Solanum americanum# Nombre Común:American black nightshade# Órgano o parte de la planta usada:Leaves# Usos más comunes:Healing, soothing, marcotic, anti-herpetic, anti-hemorrhoidal, analgesic, antipyretic, antiseptic, pediculicidal. It is used for vaginal washes and in the treatment of skin and eye conditions.# Modo de uso y preparación:Against pelvic inflammation you can use a decoction or decoction of nightshade, a bunch of this plant should be used and it is taken as common water after straining it. And to improve this decoction you can add a bunch of leaves and stems of bighorn verbena if you want. These should be boiled in a container that contains one liter of water. It is taken the same as ordinary water. It is boiled in a container that contains a liter of water and vaginal baths or washes are carried out three times a day with this boil (morning, afternoon and night).# Categorias:6,19,25,27,42,#</item>
        <item>Nombre Científico:Costus pictus# Nombre Común:Insulin plant# Órgano o parte de la planta usada:Leaves and stems # Usos más comunes:It is traditionally used for urinary conditions, such as infections, kidney stones and colic.# Modo de uso y preparación:A decoction or decoction with leaves and stems of this plant is prepared in a liter of water, it is put to boil and three glasses are taken a day.# Categorias:45,95#</item>
        <item>Nombre Científico:Moringa oleifera# Nombre Común:Moringa, Drumstick tree# Órgano o parte de la planta usada:Leaves# Usos más comunes:Regulates blood glucose levels, with anti-inflammatory activity, stimulates the immune system and is antitumor. Antimicrobial activity and bacteriostatic and bactericidal action.# Modo de uso y preparación:The leaves, flour, capsules and seeds of this plant prevent Alzheimer‘s and is cardioprotective, anticoagulant, lowers cholesterol, hypotensive and vasodilator, among many other benefits.# Categorias:21,24,36#</item>
        <item>Nombre Científico:Polypodium polypodiodies L.# Nombre Común:Resurrection fern# Órgano o parte de la planta usada:Whole plant# Usos más comunes:Diuretic, choleretic, hypotensive, general tonic and antitussive. Indicated for states in which an increase in diuresis is required; genitourinary conditions (cystitis, ureteritis, urethritis, oliguria, urolithiasis), hyperazotemia, hyperuricaemia, gout, arterial hypertension, edema, overweight accompanied by fluid retention. Prevention of arteriosclerosis; biliary dyskinesias. Bronchitis, flu, colds.# Modo de uso y preparación: In infusion one tablespoon per cup; two or three cups a day, after meals. The decoction is also made with half a bunch of leaves and half a bottle of water, and it is administered after sweetening it warm and on an empty stomach.# Categorias:30,44,57,71#</item>
        <item>Nombre Científico:Bursera graveolens # Nombre Común:Holy Wood# Órgano o parte de la planta usada:The leaves and roots# Usos más comunes:They have been used to treat ailments such as diarrhea, colds, skin conditions, and more# Modo de uso y preparación:Sassafras tea is a drink made by boiling the bark of the root of the sassafras tree. It can be combined with other herbs such as ginger, cinnamon, cloves or anise.# Categorias:53#</item>
        <item>Nombre Científico:Betabel-Beta vulgaris# Nombre Común:Beets# Órgano o parte de la planta usada:The roots# Usos más comunes:Diabetes Reduces high blood pressure, anemia # How to use and prepare: Drinking half a liter of beet, beet or beet juice helps reduce blood pressure. Beets are packed with the mineral silica, an important component for the body to use calcium efficiently. Since calcium is part of our bones and teeth, consuming a glass of beet juice a day helps to ward off diseases such as osteoporosis and brittle bones. Diabetes sufferers can satisfy their sweet cravings by adding a little beets to their diets. Being a low-glycemic vegetable (meaning it releases sugar slowly into the blood), it helps keep your blood sugar levels low while satisfying your sugar craving. Plus, this vegetable is low in calories and free. of fats, making it the perfect vegetable for diabetics. Beets contain a lot of iron. Iron aids in the formation of hemagglutinin, which is a part of the blood that helps carry oxygen and nutrients to various parts of the body. It is the iron content and not the color that helps treat anemia. Due to its high soluble fiber content, beetroot acts as an excellent laxative. Helps regulate your bowel movement by softening your stool. It also cleanses the colon and flushes harmful toxins from your stomach.# Categorias:52#</item>
        <item>Nombre Científico:Myristica fragrans# Nombre Común:Nutmeg# Órgano o parte de la planta usada:The seeds# Usos más comunes:It is used in the treatment of intestinal conditions. Stimulating. The essential oil has antifungal, antitussive and central nervous system depressant activity.# Modo de uso y preparación:To prepare the nutmeg tea, put a little water on the fire, when it starts to boil add the grated walnut, let it boil for 5 minutes, turn off the heat, let it rest for 10 minutes, strain and serve.# Categorias:30,62#</item>
        <item>Nombre Científico:Coriandrum sativum# Nombre Común:Coriander# Órgano o parte de la planta usada:Leaves# Usos más comunes:Antispasmodic and digestive. In addition, it turns out to be an excellent stimulant of the nervous system and has carminative and aperitive properties.# Modo de uso y preparación:Wash and disinfect the cilantro well. Put the water on the fire in a pot and when it starts to boil add the coriander. Boil for a couple of minutes, then steep for 10 minutes. Strain the leaves and drink the tea. # Categorias:16,40,54,62#</item>
        <item>Nombre Científico:Illicium verum# Nombre Común:Star Anise# Órgano o parte de la planta usada:The seeds and the fruits# Usos más comunes:It is allergenic, carminative, analgesic, antibacterial, antiseptic, antispasmodic, antiviral, digestive, sedative, expectorant, fungicidal, insecticidal, laxative, parasiticidal, stimulating, tonic. It can be consumed in the form of an infusion.# Modo de uso y preparación:To prepare the anise tea you must boil the water and add the anise seeds. Cover and steep for 3 to 5 minutes. Strain and drink before or after meals. In infants and children under 2 years, it is only one tablespoon of infusion, either directly or dissolved in a glass or bottle with a little water. In the case of children from 2 to 6 years old, the dose increases to four tablespoons of the infusion, either directly or dissolved in a little water. With older boys from 6 to 12 years old, half a cup of infusion can be reached. In the case of adults, a cup of infusion is good. Do not forget that the infusion must be consumed at the moment, it is not advisable to save the excess for later, because it loses its properties and can deteriorate. The water must be freshly boiled or boiled, but without maintaining the boil with the anise, to avoid concentrating the substances.# Categorias:6,11,16,27,32,40,54,62,64,88,92#</item>
        <item>Nombre Científico:Peumus boldus Molina# Nombre Común:Boldo# Órgano o parte de la planta usada:Leaves# Usos más comunes:It is a diuretic. Stimulates digestive functions by increasing bile secretion. The fresh leaves are used to treat liver and rheumatic conditions.# Modo de uso y preparación:An infusion with half a teaspoon of boldo leaves in a cup of water is used to stimulate digestive functions. The crushed leaves are applied topically to heal scrapes and sores. Hot baths and poultices are used to treat rheumatism, dropsy, syphilis, migraine, and headache. The juice of the fresh leaf is used for earaches.# Categorias:57,70,87#</item>
        <item>Nombre Científico:Indigofera suffruticosa Mill# Nombre Común:Guatemalan indigo, Anil# Órgano o parte de la planta usada:The root, the leaves.# Usos más comunes:Among the curative benefits attributed to it is that of being an antiepileptic, insecticidal, antiulcer, purgative, sedative, antiparasitic shrub; and also for the treatment of pharyngitis and against pediculosis or common scabies.# Modo de uso y preparación:To cure scabies, the crushed leaves are rubbed against the skin. Also in poultices to heal ulcers and wounds. Likewise, he attributes to the roots crushed and macerated in rum the virtue of killing the lice if the head is washed with that liquid that also destroys the nits.# Categorias:#</item>
        <item>Nombre Científico:Citrus × aurantium# Nombre Común:Bitter orange# Órgano o parte de la planta usada:The rind of the fruit and the leaves.# Usos más comunes:Cardio-circulatory, antispasmodic, diuretic, antifungal, antibacterial# Modo de uso y preparación:Boil 5-12 g of fresh leaves or fruit rind for 5 minutes. Take 300-500 mL a day divided into 2-3 doses. The same decoction is applied locally to the affected parts 2-3 times a day.# Categorias:#</item>
        <item>Nombre Científico:Heliotropium indicum Lin.# Nombre Común:Indian heliotrope, Indian Turnsole# Órgano o parte de la planta usada:Leaves# Usos más comunes:It is used to fight eczema and uric acid as well as to destroy kidney stones. In the East they use the plant for baths and for muscle aches.# Modo de uso y preparación:The cooking is done and it is taken by common water. For eczema it is used by macerating its raw branches to extract the juice; Said liquid is strained through a cloth and with a feather it is applied on the diseased part. The leaves of this herb, cooked with very little water, provide very good resolving poultices. The decoction prepared with a handful of them and a bottle of water is used with advantages for gargles, lavatories, fomentations, local baths and injections. The juice squeezed out of this fresh and freshly picked herb is considered a Vulnerary, and is administered to fill this therapeutic indication in doses of half a glass, repeated two or three times a day. Poultices made from the leaves are famous for curing bruises. The decoction of the plant is used, both externally and internally, in piles and is said to produce very good results. # Categorias:#</item>
        <item>Nombre Científico:Bryophyllum pinnatum (Lam.) Oken# Nombre Común:Air plant, Cathedral bells, Life plant# Órgano o parte de la planta usada:Leaves# Usos más comunes:Antibacterial, antifungal, healing, anti-inflammatory, vasoconstrictor and diuretic. It is used in the treatment of gingivitis, aphthous stomatitis and odontosis. Urinary antiseptic, antispasmodic, sedative, pectoral, antiepileptic, antihypertensive, ottalgic, antidisenteric and antidismenorrheic.# Modo de uso y preparación:The use of this medicinal plant can be done internally by drinking the juice of the leaves of the fresh plant and infused. Externally with a poultice, baths or washes.# Categorias:#</item>
        <item>Nombre Científico:Sideritis tragoriganum# Nombre Común:Ironwort, Mountain tea# Órgano o parte de la planta usada:Aerial part.# Usos más comunes:Indoor use for Gastritis, ulcers and enterocolitis. Infections of the urinary tract. Exterior, antiseptic and anti-inflammatory, both in gargles and in dermal washes (sores, ulcers, psoriasis, etc.) and eye (conjunctivitis, blepharitis).# Modo de uso y preparación:Infusion.# Categorias:#</item>
        <item>Nombre Científico:Capraria biflora# Nombre Común:Capraria# Órgano o parte de la planta usada:Leaves# Usos más comunes:It is widely used by women to treat conditions of the uterus and ovaries, such as vaginal discharge, bleeding from the womb, some sexually transmitted diseases such as gonorrhea and even to prevent cancer in this area. Medicinal effects are also attributed to it in diseases of the digestive system, in high fevers, colds, hypertension, diabetes, acne and in cases of inflammation caused by insect bites. Its main components are biflorin, which acts as a fungicide and antibiotic, harpagida and capriarioside, which are analgesic.# Modo de uso y preparación:It is taken as an infusion# Categorias:#</item>
        <item>Nombre Científico:Jatropha gossypifolia# Nombre Común:Bellyache bush, Black physicnut# Órgano o parte de la planta usada:The leaves, fruits and roots# Usos más comunes:The leaves are used as antispasmodic, antidiabetic, antiasthmatic, antivenom, and emmenagogue. The roots are used for their diuretic and stomachic properties and the seeds as a cholagogue. Latex is applied to burns.# Modo de uso y preparación:The oil extracted from seeds and fruits is used to make concoctions that incite vomiting as well as the cooking of leaves. Latex is used to heal wounds and burns and to treat skin diseases. The leaves also have anti-inflammatory properties. Consumption of this species for medicinal purposes should be moderate due to its toxicity. # Categorias:1,16,59#</item>
        <item>Nombre Científico:Amaranthus spinosus # Nombre Común:Spiny amaranth, Spiny pigweed# Órgano o parte de la planta usada:The leaves and the root. # Usos más comunes:It is attributed properties such as sneezing, purifying, diuretic, emmenagogue, against bladder inflammations and rheumatic pain.# Modo de uso y preparación:It is used in the form of decoction and poultices. The decoction of the root taken by cups is used to heal the pressure of blood or disinterestedness, it is used as a cleanser in the form of syrup. The decoction with the leaves is used in enemas, lotions, fomentations or local baths, be it alone. The leaves cooked with very little water and properly ground, constitute very good poultices. Bledo blanco leaves passed by candle and then cushioned are used in the cure of inflamed sores.# Categorias:49,57,59#</item>
        <item>Nombre Científico:Melia azedarach L# Nombre Común:Chinaberry tree, Pride of India # Órgano o parte de la planta usada:The seeds, stems and leaves# Usos más comunes:It should be used topically in case of Scabies (scabies); for Pediculosis capitis (the well-known lice) and also as an insecticide.# Modo de uso y preparación:Many people prepare a decoction or decoction with seeds of paradise and leave it to rest. Other people use a can of water in which they put a lot of seeds of paradise, keep it for 3 or 4 days and it ends up being a powerful insecticide against cockroaches and other insects. A decoction of stems and leaves, 3 large bunches that are boiled in a liter of water for 10 minutes and with that they faced skin ailment with very good results.# Categorias:#</item>
        <item>Nombre Científico:Turnera ulmifolia# Nombre Común:Ramgoat dashalong, Yellow alder# Órgano o parte de la planta usada:Leaves# Usos más comunes:Expectorants, facilitates menstruation, reduces or eliminates pain, improves digestion. # Modo de uso y preparación:The infusion is prepared by boiling 5 to 6 flowers in a cup of water; They are used to relieve the pain that accompanies menstruation, to facilitate digestion and for other gastrointestinal disorders. The infusion is prepared by adding a bunch of flowers, or flowers and leaves, in a liter of boiling water, it is used to relieve headaches or as an expectorant. In both cases you should take 1 or 2 cups a day.# Categorias:#</item>
        <item>Nombre Científico:Cinnamomum camphora# Nombre Común:Camphorwood, Camphor laurel# Órgano o parte de la planta usada:Leaves# Usos más comunes:In external application it can relieve headaches and neuralgia. (preferably with camphor alcohol).# Modo de uso y preparación:Decoction; boil for no more than 3 minutes 60-80 g of fresh leaves per liter of water. Apply locally 2-3 times a day.# Categorias:78#</item>
        <item>Nombre Científico:Myrica cerifera L.# Nombre Común:Southern wax myrtle, Southern bayberry# Órgano o parte de la planta usada:The root bark# Usos más comunes:It is considered astringent. The decoction of the leaves is used for stimulating baths and to heal sores and ulcers. Root bark is considered tonic and stimulating.# Modo de uso y preparación:Decoction; boil for or less than 5 minutes, 20 g of the crushed root bark or in shavings, in 2 liters of water. Apply locally 2-3 times a day.# Categorias:35,62,92#</item>
        <item>Nombre Científico:Simarouba glauca DC.# Nombre Común:Paradise-tree, Dysentery-bark, Bitterwood# Órgano o parte de la planta usada:The leaves, bark and root.# Usos más comunes:It is considered insecticide, antimalarial, astringent, digestive, anthelmintic (bark) and antidiarrheal. It is used in case of nervous colitis and skin conditions. The leaf tincture has antiamebic activity. The crushed leaves are applied topically to treat skin conditions and some forms of cancer.# Modo de uso y preparación:Traditionally, an infusion of a bunch of leaves is prepared in a bottle of boiling water. Apply locally on the affected parts 2 or 3 times a day.# Categorias:14,18,35,54#</item>
        <item>Nombre Científico:Guazuma ulmifolia Lam# Nombre Común:West Indian elm, Bay cedar# Órgano o parte de la planta usada:Fruits, leaves, trunk# Usos más comunes:The fruit is eaten raw in the treatment of anemia. It is used to treat burns caused by guao. The decoction is said to be effective against hemorrhoids and to possess emollient and astringent properties; it is also used to treat bruises and bumps. Diuretic and anti-flu.# Modo de uso y preparación:The tea of this plant can be easily prepared by placing 2 to 3 tablespoons of dried husks from the trunk of the plant in 1 liter of boiling water, boil for 10 to 15 minutes. Strain and drink 2 or 3 times a day. # Categorias:35,57,61#</item>
        <item>Nombre Científico:Ricinus communis# Nombre Común:Castor bean, Castor oil plant# Órgano o parte de la planta usada: The oil that is obtained from its seeds# Usos más comunes:Digestive, laxative # How to use and prepare: Castor oil is used as a cathartic (laxative) in the usual dose of 15 ml for adults.# Categorias:18,73#</item>
        <item>Nombre Científico:Hibiscus elatus Sw.# Nombre Común:Blue mahoe# Órgano o parte de la planta usada:The leaves, the flowers and the root# Usos más comunes:It has bronchodilator properties. In addition, it is traditionally used in the treatment of hemorrhoids and as a Vulnerary and disinfectant. The root, as a laxative. The flowers, as antitumor drugs.# Modo de uso y preparación:Its flowers are used in the preparation of syrup (Imefasma) that acts as a bronchodilator in the respiratory system. It is used to relieve gastrointestinal and respiratory ailments; To soothe rheumatic and muscular pain, an alcohol-based dose and majagua flowers are used. The cooking of its leaves heal hemorrhoids. It has analgesic properties for the ears and bronchi, as well as emollients, as it softens tumors.# Categorias:98#</item>
        <item>Nombre Científico:Mirabilis jalapa L.# Nombre Común:Marvel of Peru, Four o‘clock flower# Órgano o parte de la planta usada:The root# Usos más comunes:It is digestive, the use of the juice of the flowers is reported to relieve earaches, cure herpes and remove freckles from the face. The root powder is anthelmintic.# Modo de uso y preparación:Decoction; boiled for no more than 1 minute the equivalent of a teaspoon of the shredded root for each cup of water. Let stand 15 minutes before drinking. Drink a cup at night.# Categorias:18,54#</item>
        <item>Nombre Científico:Vetiveria zizanioides (L.) Nash# Nombre Común:Vetiver, Khus # Órgano o parte de la planta usada:The roots# Usos más comunes:Antifungal. Traditionally, the decoction of the roots is used for the topical treatment of skin eruptions and hemorrhoids orally, as a refresher during fevers. Reduced to dust for bilious ailments. The essential oil in friction for rheumatism and neuralgia.# Modo de uso y preparación:Prepare a decoction with approximately 25 g of roots per 1l of water. Boil for no less than 10 min. # Categorias:17#</item>
        <item>Nombre Científico:Rhamnus frangula# Nombre Común:Alder buckthorn, Glossy buckthorn# Órgano o parte de la planta usada:The crust# Usos más comunes:The second dry bark of the bush is used, which is indicated against constipation. In cases of poisoning, it causes vomiting; regulates the functioning of the stomach and intestines and is the best remedy against constipation that often accompanies pregnancy, since it solves it without risks to the health of the pregnant woman and the child. Stimulates the functioning of the liver and spleen; solves hemorrhoids and minor circulatory disorders. # Modo de uso y preparación:The arraclán infusion is prepared with 5 or 6 inches of chopped bark per liter of water. The decoction is prepared with the same dose that will be left to boil for half an hour and marinate for 12 hours. For external use (compresses, sitz baths, enemas, etc.), half a handful of bark per liter of water.# Categorias:#</item>
        <item>Nombre Científico:Piper aduncun L.# Nombre Común:Spiked pepper, Matico# Órgano o parte de la planta usada:Leaves and stems# Usos más comunes:It is used as a decoction or decoction for cases of arthritis, osteoarthritis, kidney disease and migraine.# Modo de uso y preparación:The cooking is prepared with a bunch of leaves and stems that are boiled in a container that contains a bottle of water. After straining or filtering with an antiseptic cloth, it is swallowed in small cups two or three times a day.# Categorias:34#</item>
        <item>Nombre Científico:Solanum mammosum L.# Nombre Común:Nipplefruit, Fox head, Cow‘s udder# Órgano o parte de la planta usada:The leaves and the fruit. # Usos más comunes:The decoction of the leaves is used as a remedy for diseases of the kidneys and bladder. The decoction of its leaves is used to clean wounds and sores, and the powder of the leaves is used to heal wounds and sores and to heal mainly the caused by dog bites.# Modo de uso y preparación:The crushed fruit, in decoction with all the juice, is used to cure asthma, drinking a cup at the beginning of the attack and four more during the following 24 hours (two fruits per cup). There is also friction on the chest with the juice. The cooking of the leaves, half a bunch for a bottle of water, is used in the East, at the rate of three cups a day, as a cleanser when skin eruptions appear. With these leaves cooked in little water, sedative poultices are prepared that are put on inflamed and sore parts.# Categorias:#</item>
        <item>Nombre Científico:Zuelania guidonia# Nombre Común:Zuelania# Órgano o parte de la planta usada:The leaves and bark# Usos más comunes:The bark put in water is drunk as common water to purify the blood. If it is sprayed, it is applied to heal wounds. Resin is a powerful laxative.# Modo de uso y preparación:The resin that flows from the trunk spontaneously or by white and aromatic incision, is diuretic at a dose of 3 or 4 grams and is used as a purifying agent in the form of a pill, especially in cases of venereal diseases, ”There are testimonies that support the usefulness of making a Aqueous maceration with peels from the trunk or thick branches of guaguasi and three pills with the resin that acts as a purgative or strong laxative. The bark, as well as the leaves of Guaguasi have a bitter taste and after being reduced to a powder when crushed in a mortar, they are used to heal sores on the skin. Likewise, a decoction or decoction is prepared with a bunch of bark that works as a kind of analgesic liniment when rheumatic pains appear.# Categorias:73#</item>
        <item>Nombre Científico:Tropaeolum majus# Nombre Común:Nasturtium, Indian cress# Órgano o parte de la planta usada:The leaves, flowers and seeds# Usos más comunes:The active parts of the plant have adequate antibiotic and bacteriological action in urinary tract, flu and dermal infections. The leaves and flowers are useful in salads against vitamin deficiency. It is a plant that is used in difficult digestions, it is not used in the form of decoction or cooking, but in the form of maceration because the heat destroys the vitamins and other active principles that constitute the greatest therapeutic virtue of nasturtium# Modo de uso y preparación:The maceration is prepared with a bunch of leaves, stems and cappuccino seeds, they are crushed and placed in a container containing a liter of boiled water, kept at rest for at least 2 hours, ingested an 8-ounce glass in fast.# Categorias:#</item>
        <item>Nombre Científico:Calycophyllum candidissimum# Nombre Común:Dagame # Órgano o parte de la planta usada:The aerial part# Usos más comunes:It is used medicinally mainly in gargles to deal with sore throats. When ingested, it helps wonderfully to heal affected parts of the throat in a short time.# Modo de uso y preparación:The infusion of the aerial part is given as a febrifuge.# Categorias:#</item>
        <item>Nombre Científico:Cynodon dactylon# Nombre Común:Bermuda grass, Bahama grass # Órgano o parte de la planta usada:The leaves and rhizomes.# Usos más comunes:It is said that the root is used satisfactorily as a purifying, diuretic, expectorant and febrifuge.Hypotensive, against gastralgia, antidiarrheal and in nervous affections# Modo de uso y preparación:The decoction or maceration is drunk three or four times a day.# Categorias:49,64,66#</item>
        <item>Nombre Científico:Cecropia peltata# Nombre Común:Trumpet tree, Snakewood# Órgano o parte de la planta usada:Leaves# Usos más comunes:The astringent and corrosive latex. It is used against warts, corns, herpes, ulcers, dysentery and venereal diseases. The bark is antiblenorrhagic, the roots antibiliosis and the fruit emulsifying. The leaves are analgesic, emmenagogue, antiasthmatic. They are used in conditions of the liver and dropsy. In general, it is stated that it has hypostenizing, cardiovascular, diuretic, skin softening, tonic-capillary and healing properties.# Modo de uso y preparación:A fresh leaf is boiled every day and a cup of the decoction is taken every 2 hours for 1 or 2 weeks to relieve asthma.# Categorias:6,10,35,57#</item>
        <item>Nombre Científico:Lawsonia inermis L# Nombre Común:Hina, The henna tree# Órgano o parte de la planta usada:The flowers, leaves, bark and roots# Usos más comunes:The leaves are macerated in alcohol and applied in poultices to cure headaches. The infusion of the leaves is taken for tummy ache and that of the flowers as a sedative. If it is taken as common water, it is useful in the treatment of hypertension.# Modo de uso y preparación:The leaves and flowers macerated in wine to combat hysteria, at the rate of a daily glass. Other traditional practices positively support the use of decoction or cooking with a handful of shells from the trunk or thick branches of Resedá that are poured into a container with half a liter of water. It is placed on the fire for 8 to 10 minutes and after boiling it is strained and three glasses are ingested, morning, afternoon and night. This natural remedy is useful for cases of hysteria and insomnia.# Categorias:88#</item>
        <item>Nombre Científico:Trichilia Hirta Linneo.# Nombre Común:Guaita # Órgano o parte de la planta usada:Whole plant# Usos más comunes:Anti-inflammatory, antigiardial, purifying, immunostimulating, antitumor, purgative, energetic.# Modo de uso y preparación:Jubabán infusion. Take a piece of Jubabán root and wash it properly to remove impurities. Then water is boiled in a container, and as soon as it reaches the boiling point, remove from the heat and add the Jubatan root. Let the infusion rest to cool, then pack and drink. Consume three cups of coffee a day of this infusion. Some authors refer to the use of all the parts of the plant for the infusion, not only the Jubabán root and the cooking of the leaves for baths against ulcers. # Categorias:21,49#</item>
        <item>Nombre Científico:Anacardium occidentale L.# Nombre Común:Cashew tree# Órgano o parte de la planta usada:The fruit, the seeds and the leaves# Usos más comunes:The pulp of the fruit is used as an astringent and antidiarrheal, pectoral and useful against blood sputum. Roasted seeds are considered a powerful aphrodisiac. The infusion of the leaves is offered as an antidiarrheal.# Modo de uso y preparación:In cases of the so-called acidosis in children, a decoction with cashew leaves was used, it is taken almost cold, slightly sweetened and for diabetes prepare a decoction with cohollos or tender cashew leaves taken without sugar like common water. It is used to face cases of diabetes this remedy can look for the white cashew stick. A piece is washed well to remove impurities, it is divided into pieces and poured into a container that contains a liter or two of water, depending on the size of the stick, it is left to rest and after that it is strained and taken as ordinary water. The powder of the roasted seed with milk is used as a stomach tonic# Categorias:14,35,81#</item>
        <item>Nombre Científico:Spondias mombin L.# Nombre Común:Yellow mombin, Hog plum# Órgano o parte de la planta usada:The bark and the fruit # Usos más comunes:The infusion of the bark is taken as an astringent and to wash infected wounds. The fruit ingested in high doses is a powerful emetic. The decoction of the bark is recommended to treat hemorrhoids.# Modo de uso y preparación:To treat malaria, cook 10 grams of this in half a liter of water and take it during the day, to treat intestinal ulcers the infusion of the bark is used, as healing washes are made with the cooking of the bark or applying the juice of this on the affected part, to treat lechmaniasis the bark is ground, then toasted and the resulting ash is applied on the affected area. The decoction of the root is used in baths to treat hemorrhoids and vaginal infections; drink is used against diarrhea.# Categorias:35#</item>
        <item>Nombre Científico:Apium graveolens L.# Nombre Común:Celery# Órgano o parte de la planta usada: The aerial part# Usos más comunes:The juice of the aerial part with honey is taken to cure liver diseases. And also as an antianemic.# Modo de uso y preparación:You just have to blend 1 stalk of celery with 1 glass of water and that‘s it. You can add other ingredients if you want. Serve and consume immediately.# Categorias:9#</item>
        <item>Nombre Científico:Tillandsia recurvata L.# Nombre Común:Small ballmoss, Ball moss# Órgano o parte de la planta usada:Leaves# Usos más comunes:The infusion of the leaves mixed with pigeon pea and Paraná yerba is recommended to treat giardiasis. The crushed leaves mixed with oil are applied locally to cure hemorrhoids.# Modo de uso y preparación:As common water and in boils 2 or 3 times a day. It stores rainwater at the base of its leaves that serves to quench thirst.# Categorias:#</item>
        <item>Nombre Científico:Bursera simaruba L. # Nombre Común:Gumbo-limbo, Copperwood# Órgano o parte de la planta usada:The leaves, bark and shoots# Usos más comunes:The decoction of leaves and shoots is registered as anticatarrhal and febrifuge; externally they are applied as a poultice in the treatment of stomach colds. The bark has the same properties as the leaves, but it must be used with care (especially in children) because it is very hot. The local application of resin is very useful to extract thorns from the skin.# Modo de uso y preparación:For the decoction, it is prepared with a bunch of the root, the peel, the leaves and the bud (which is also antispasmodic) and half a bottle of water. Let it boil for no less than 20 minutes, and after straining and sweetening it is administered by cups at the end of the day.# Categorias:12,16,66#</item>
        <item>Nombre Científico:Zebrina pendula# Nombre Común:Inch plant, Wandering Jew# Órgano o parte de la planta usada:Leaves# Usos más comunes: The juice obtained from the leaves is applied externally as an anti-hemorrhagic.# Modo de uso y preparación:It is used in the form of fomentations on the injured areas, a decoction is prepared with a bunch of the plant in a liter and a quarter of water. For corns, apply the leaves on the affected area.# Categorias:#</item>
        <item>Nombre Científico:Jatropha curcas L. # Nombre Común:Physic nut, Barbados nut, Bubble bush# Órgano o parte de la planta usada:The leaves and the seeds# Usos más comunes:Poultices made from the leaves are applied to treat eczema. Latex is a healing agent. The oil extracted from the seeds is a strong laxative; very toxic too. # Modo de uso y preparación:By pulling a leaf from the plant, the liquid that the plant spills when detaching the leaf is placed in the wound and after a few minutes the effects of the substance are noticed, it causes a slight pain although compared to alcohol it is less. Make sure that it does not get on the clothes, since the stain is very difficult to remove. As a purgative; about 3 pine nut seeds are chewed with a half liter of water, this is enough, since the excess of seeds can cause dehydration and as a consequence loss of consciousness. After ingesting the effect is expected and should not be taken again within seven days as a precaution.# Categorias:42#</item>
        <item>Nombre Científico:Tapetes erecta L# Nombre Común:Mexican marigold, Aztec marigold# Órgano o parte de la planta usada:Flowers and leaves# Usos más comunes:The flowers are used for diseases of the chest and in cooking against pneumonia. Also for stomach pains, in addition this plant is also used in remedies for spleen, stomach, and liver conditions, also as a vermifuge. # Modo de uso y preparación:The decoction of the flowers is used as a pectoral and anticatarrhal. The infusion of the leaves and flowers, as a vermifuge.# Categorias:#</item>
        <item>Nombre Científico:Basella rubra L.# Nombre Común:Malabar spinach, Vine spinach# Órgano o parte de la planta usada:The leaves and the root# Usos más comunes: The leaves are applied externally in the form of a poultice to treat inflammations. The root is provided to dissolve external and internal tumors. In addition to the nutritional elements it has, spinach is recommended, alone or in combination with other vegetables, for liver diseases, against high blood pressure, anemia, constipation, hemorrhoids, rheumatism, asthma, flu and obesity.# Modo de uso y preparación:Its most common use is as a salad, but it can also be eaten boiled with other vegetables in soups and broths or accompanied by some meat seasoned with seasonings.# Categorias:#</item>
        <item>Nombre Científico:Varronia globosa# Nombre Común:Curacao bush# Órgano o parte de la planta usada:The aerial part# Usos más comunes:The decoction of the aerial part is administered internally as a blood purifier and as a hemostatic if applied externally as a wash. # Modo de uso y preparación:The use of the decoction of this plant helps the body rid itself of toxins. Prepare 50 grams of sarsaparilla root, a bunch of grass and stems of the yerba de la blood and a large fragment of hump root that is divided into small portions. All this is boiled in a liter of water over low heat, for 10 minutes, it is strained and it is taken 3 to 4 glasses a day as natural water.# Categorias:#</item>
        <item>Nombre Científico:Pinus caribaea Morelet# Nombre Común:Caribbean pine# Órgano o parte de la planta usada:Leaves # Usos más comunes:Wood sawdust combined with guayacán sawdust in alcoholic maceration for antirheumatic friction. Decoction of leaves and / or wood orally for impotence, bronchitis, gonorrhea and genito-urinary inflammation. Resin from the trunk for eczema. Antifungal leaves (decoction).# Modo de uso y preparación:Decoction; boil 100 g of fresh leaves in 1 liter of water for 5 minutes. Stand for no less than 15 minutes. Apply locally to the affected area 2-3 times a day.# Categorias:#</item>
        <item>Nombre Científico:Teucrium cubense Jacq.# Nombre Común:Small coastal germander, Dwarf germander# Órgano o parte de la planta usada:The aerial part# Usos más comunes:It is used in the field as a tonic and febrifuge. It has been recommended against chronic splenitis or chronic infarction of the spleen that usually follows intermittent fever; and it is also applied successfully against edema or swelling of the legs, which recognizes the same pathological cause. They use the decoction of the leaves for stomach pain. Elsewhere they use it for chilling fevers. It is also said to be abortifacient.# Modo de uso y preparación:En infusión y decocción de la parte aérea.# Categorias:#</item>
        <item>Nombre Científico:Guaiacum officinale L.# Nombre Común:Roughbark, Lignum-vitae, Guaiacwood# Órgano o parte de la planta usada:The crust# Usos más comunes: Against rheumatism and anesthetic.# Modo de uso y preparación:Its use is in alcoholic maceration of its bark for friction against rheumatism. The crushed bark is applied when there is toothache as an anesthetic.# Categorias:87#</item>
        <item>Nombre Científico:Eupatorium aromatisans# Nombre Común:Trebol# Órgano o parte de la planta usada:The leaves and the roots# Usos más comunes: They are used in the treatment of headache, dropsy, rheumatism and its roots in the treatment of toothache.# Modo de uso y preparación: Application of the oiled blade on the forehead. Accidents leaves poured hot ram bait application of the blade and blows to the head# Categorias:87#</item>
        <item>Nombre Científico:Phyla scaberrima # Nombre Común:Aztec sweet herb, Bushy lippia# Órgano o parte de la planta usada:Leaves# Usos más comunes:The juice and infusions of the leaves are applied as a pectoral and stomach and to cure bronchitis and cough. # Modo de uso y preparación:Against asthma or suffocation they use the cooking of 100g of leaves for a liter of water.# Categorias:#</item>
        <item>Nombre Científico:Lippia alba # Nombre Común:Bushy matgrass, Bushy lippia# Órgano o parte de la planta usada:Leaves and flowers# Usos más comunes:It is taken as an anticatarrhal, antispasmodic and febrifuge.# Modo de uso y preparación:Make an infusion with the leaves and flowers# Categorias:12,16,66#</item>
        <item>Nombre Científico:Corchorus siliquosus L.# Nombre Común:Jute mallow leaves# Órgano o parte de la planta usada:The aerial part# Usos más comunes: It is considered anti-inflammatory externally and internally, and a powerful febrifuge.# Modo de uso y preparación:Decoction of the aerial part.# Categorias:21,66#</item>
        <item>Nombre Científico:Scoparia dulcis L. # Nombre Común:Licorice weed, Goatweed, Scoparia-weed# Órgano o parte de la planta usada:The whole plant # Usos más comunes: It is taken to treat diarrhea and normalize menstruation.# Modo de uso y preparación:Decoction of the whole plant# Categorias:#</item>
        <item>Nombre Científico:Cordia gerascanthus L.# Nombre Común:Varia# Órgano o parte de la planta usada:The leaves and the root# Usos más comunes: As anticatarrhal and against respiratory diseases. It is useful in the treatment of epilepsy.# Modo de uso y preparación:The infusion of the leaves as anticatarral and respiratory diseases. Decoction of the root to treat epilepsy# Categorias:12#</item>
        <item>Nombre Científico:Pluchea carolinensis # Nombre Común:Cure for all, Bushy fleabane# Órgano o parte de la planta usada:The leaves and stems# Usos más comunes: Anticatarrhal, digestive, febrifuge and menstrual disorders.# Modo de uso y preparación:The juice is drunk macerated with coffee as an anticatarrhal and to cure sore throats and hoarseness. The leaves are applied to the forehead and temple to combat headaches. The decoction of the leaves and stems is drunk# Categorias:12,54,66#</item>
        <item>Nombre Científico:Maranta arundinacea L.# Nombre Común:Arrowroot, Maranta# Órgano o parte de la planta usada:The root# Usos más comunes: It is used to treat blisters and infections of the urethra. It is also nutritious, digestive, and antidiarrheal.# Modo de uso y preparación:The decoction of the rhizome is used to cure blisters and infections of the urethra. Starch is considered nutritious, digestive, and antidiarrheal.# Categorias:14,54#</item>
        <item>Nombre Científico:Guarea guidonia# Nombre Común:Guarea# Órgano o parte de la planta usada:The whole plant# Usos más comunes:Haemostatic. It is known as the most powerful anti-hemorrhagic drug in Cuba. # Modo de uso y preparación:Decoction of the whole plant# Categorias:#</item>
        <item>Nombre Científico:Trichilia glabra L.# Nombre Común:Trichilia# Órgano o parte de la planta usada:The leaves and the fruit# Usos más comunes: Anti-asthmatic. Diuretic and good against kidney stones. Anti-rheumatic.# Modo de uso y preparación:It is placed under the mattress of the asthmatic‘s bed. The infusion of the leaves is diuretic and good against kidney stones. The fruit juice in alcohol is indicated for antirheumatic friction.# Categorias:10,26,57#</item>
    </array>
    <array name="dolencias">
        <item> Nombre:Acidity# Descripcion:Heartburn, reflux (also popularly known as heartburn, heartburn or simply burning) consists of a burning sensation that begins in the lower part of the chest and can spread to the throat.# Remedios:Sodium bicarbonate is a natural remedy, which has the ability to neutralize the acids accumulated in the stomach, especially when they produce a burning sensation. It is included in the catalog of natural alkalis, since its pH is higher than 7.0 and it can regulate acidity levels. To consume, dilute 5 grams of bicarbonate in a glass of water, and drink it slowly, avoid consuming more than the recommended dose, it could be counterproductive. In addition, it is advisable to consult with the doctor who follows your consumption history. Taking rolled oats also helps neutralize heartburn. Simply put a few oatmeal flakes in a small bowl and add enough water to make it wet. Dilute a tablespoon of potato juice in a glass of water. You get the juice by grating the potato.% Dilute a tablespoon of apple cider vinegar in a glass of water and drink slowly. % This ginger tea can provide us with well-being in cases of heartburn. You just have to add a teaspoon of grated ginger in a cup and add very hot water. Cover it and let it rest for 5 minutes. Then you can add a little stevia to sweeten, cane syrup, etc.% Anise will help you fight acidity and improve digestion. In addition to being effective, it is very pleasant to take, if you chew the anise seeds it will leave you with a very pleasant taste in your mouth. An infusion of cinnamon can be another great natural remedy to improve heartburn. You can combine it with other remedies such as ginger infusion and thus you get better and faster results. This home remedy also helps us relieve heartburn. Another natural and simple remedy that we can easily prepare at home is lettuce tea. Cut 3 lettuce leaves into strips, put them in a bowl and add boiling water. Cover it and let it rest for 10 minutes. Then strain and drink little by little. You can add a little cinnamon to sweeten, as well as stevia. Aloe vera or aloe vera juice can be taken before or after food. And it is that having an aloe vera or aloe plant at home is the best we can do. This excellent medicinal plant goes for everything from improving gum health, healing wounds to fighting heartburn. You can take a piece of aloe about 2 centimeters square as it is, swallowing it. Or you can also prepare the natural pineapple or papaya juice and add the piece of aloe vera and beat it and take it with the fruit. Fennel has been used since ancient times to promote digestive processes and in cases of heartburn, this medicinal plant with a delicious bulb helps you relieve the annoying burning.% Include fresh parsley in your recipes and you will see that indigestion is mitigated or eliminated. It can also be taken as an infusion after a meal if there is heartburn. Papaya promotes digestion and is able to calm the discomfort caused by heartburn or heartburn. It is also beneficial in cases of gastritis. % Pineapple is another great ally for good digestion and heavy meals. When you have discomfort, do not hesitate to take one or two slices of pineapple to relieve them and feel better. The Apple will help you with digestion and heartburn. Have an apple (of the variety that you like the most) and you will see how the discomfort of burning is improved. Easy, cheap and natural. </item>
        <item>Nombre:Acne# Descripcion:It is a chronic inflammatory skin disease characterized by the formation of pimples, pimples, which appear mainly on the face and upper part of the trunk.# Remedios:An excellent home remedy to eliminate acne on the face is to control the oil on the skin, and use products on the skin that can reduce inflammation of the pimples and unclog pores. The good options are rice, honey and mint tea because they contain medicinal properties capable of acting in this type of situation. To reduce pimples is to apply daily a homemade mask prepared with rice and honey because these ingredients reduce inflammation and clarify the skin, maintaining good hydration.% Watercress, in addition to being an excellent source of minerals such as calcium and iodine, is rich in vitamins A and E that help fight acne. Pennyroyal also has many vitamins, and avocado has beneficial fats to the body that leave the skin softer. Since sodium bicarbonate has anti-inflammatory and antiseptic action, it acts as an exfoliator for the skin, also helping to regulate its pH. It is enough to place two tablespoons of baking soda in a container and add water and stir until a homogeneous paste is formed, then it should be applied to the face and kept for a few minutes, then you should wash your face with water.% Perform light massages on the skin with turbinate sugar, previously moistened. Then wash with fresh water. % Other traditional practices refer to the use of decoction or cooking with a bunch of leaves and stems of the plant known for wonder that is boiled in a container that contains a liter of water. Likewise, massages are carried out with the fingertips on the parts of the body where there are spots on the skin. The juice or juice of the sugar cane is used, that is to say, of the guarapo, after cleaning the skin, this application is made with the fingertips from the bottom upwards gently and in a circular way for 5 minutes, it is removed with plenty of water without using soap, this can be done in the morning, afternoon, night and before going to bed.</item>
        <item>Nombre:Allergies# Descripcion:Allergies are not caused by a virus, but by allergens to which the body reacts, and generally last as long as it is exposed to the agent that causes it. They usually last longer than a cold, but the symptoms are similar. It can cause sneezing, a runny nose, and watery eyes.# Remedios:Irrigating the nose with a saline solution would help soften the mucosa and clean the pollen or dust that caused the allergic reaction, thereby relieving sneezing and runny nose. Honey has pollen particles, so by consuming it you are exposing yourself to small doses of the allergen, making your body get used to it and stop taking it as a threat; this would reduce the strength of allergic reactions.% Green tea has a compound that would block the production of histamine and IgE, substances that trigger allergy symptoms. % Taking an infusion of peppermint or inhaling its essential oil would be useful to relieve symptoms of allergy to pollen or dust: Peppermint contains a substance that would block the production of histamine, relieving sneezing and a runny nose.</item>
        <item>Nombre:Arthritis# Descripcion:Rheumatoid arthritis is an inflammation of the joints due to an alteration of the immune system, which causes a lot of pain and discomfort and which, if left untreated, can leave the fingers and other joints deformed.# Remedios:Sage and rosemary tea helps reduce pain caused by arthritis and rheumatism, being a great natural anti-inflammatory.% Massaging your joints with this essential oil blend is also a great natural way to feel better. Turmeric tea is rich in antioxidants that increase immunity, reducing pain and inflammation caused by arthritis.% Another good natural solution for arthritis is to eat a salad plate garnished with 1 tablespoon of apple cider vinegar. Apple cider vinegar is made from fermented apple juice and its enzymes dissolve calcium deposits in the joints, making it ideal for fighting this disease. Try preparing a salad with lettuce leaves, tomato, onion and watercress, and seasoning with olive oil and apple cider vinegar. Pour ginger slices into a bottle of rum or brandy and wait 15 days. At the end of these, ingesting one ounce (30 mL) twice a day.% Boil and mash sweet potato (preferably yellow) to make a sweet potato. Prepare a ginger decoction. While both are boiling, mix them looking for a suitable consistency and add ground cinnamon. Stir well to ensure proper distribution of the substances. Sweeten them discreetly with honey. It should be consumed two or three tablespoons two or three times a day.% Place 3 heads of raw garlic cut transversely in a bottle of white liquor for a week. Taking 30 mL daily on an empty stomach or 3 hours after the last meal. If it is taken as a means of preventing crises, it should be done from Monday to Friday, suspending it on Saturdays and Sundays. If you are in crisis, it should be taken interrupted until it disappears.</item>
        <item>Nombre:Anemia# Descripcion:Anemia is not a disease, but a sign that can be caused by multiple causes, one of the most frequent is iron deficiency, either due to insufficient intake of this mineral in the diet, or due to excessive losses due to bleeding.# Remedios:It is recommended to include foods rich in iron in the diet, which are generally dark in color such as beets, plums, black beans and even chocolate.% Pineapple juice with parsley is excellent for fighting anemia because parsley has iron and pineapple has vitamin C that enhances the absorption of iron. % Orange, carrot and beet juice are excellent for fighting anemia because it is rich in iron. % Prune juice is excellent for fighting anemia because it is rich in vitamin C, and therefore enhances the absorption of iron from foods of plant origin.</item>
        <item>Nombre:Anxiety# Descripcion:Feeling anxious is a normal human reaction to situations of stress or uncertainty. However, despite being an adaptive reaction, it can sometimes interfere with the proper functioning of people‘s lives and can create great discomfort.# Remedios:Although green tea is a stimulant, some studies have shown that it is beneficial for anxiety. Mainly because it stimulates brain neurotransmitters that induce relaxation, thanks to L-theanine.% The infusion of Passionflower acts as an anxiolytic and is a calming and relaxing that comes from the passion flower. It was used by the Aztecs centuries ago for its analgesic and sedative effects. It is also indicated in cases of depression, as it produces a slight euphoria. It is also used for insomnia, headache or tachycardia. Physical exercise should be a habit that everyone should practice because its benefits are numerous. Among them, we can find that it reduces cortisol levels in the body, helps to fall asleep, releases endorphins that make us feel good and reduces stress and anxiety levels. Yoga has a number of psychological benefits as well as physical ones. Its practice has a positive impact on stress and anxiety, as it reduces the levels of cortisol, a hormone that is released in response to stress. By practicing yoga we can lower the levels of this hormone to reduce stress and, therefore, anxiety. A 20-minute walk on the beach or in the woods, as indicated by a study carried out by Japanese researchers, helps reduce stress and anxiety.</item>
        <item>Nombre:Nephritic Colic, Kidney Stones# Descripcion:Kidney stones, also called kidney stones, are hard deposits that form in the kidneys. The stones have to travel through the urinary tract to leave the body, which is known as the elimination of kidney stones, something that can be quite painful.# Remedios:Drinking water is one of the easiest ways to prevent and treat kidney stones. Most health authorities recommend drinking 64 ounces (oz) or eight glasses of water per day. Drinking 12 glasses per day can help facilitate the elimination or slow the growth of deposits in the kidneys. Lemons contain citrate, a compound that helps break down calcium deposits and slow their growth. Two 5-ounce (0.15L) glasses, the first on an empty stomach first thing in the morning and the other a few hours before dinner, can help undo the smallest stones. Basil contains compounds known to help stabilize uric acid levels, making it harder for kidney stones to form. In addition, it contains acetic acid, a chemical known to help dissolve stones. One teaspoon of basil extract or pure juice a day can help prevent and treat kidney stones% Apple cider vinegar also contains citric acid which can help dissolve calcium deposits. Extra virgin olive oil is a thick and rich oil that can help facilitate the elimination of kidney stones by lubricating the urinary tract. You should also avoid consuming calcium, chocolate, and caffeine% Chancapiedra tea helps eliminate kidney stones due to its diuretic action.% Celery or also called Spanish celery or celery, has excellent diuretic and calming properties, eliminating toxins that contribute to the formation of kidney stones and soothe pain. Mix one or more celery stalks with water and drink the juice throughout the day. Another important thing for the treatment of kidney pain is important to drink 2L of water a day, as this helps to eliminate bacteria and clean the kidneys. It is also important to rest so that the body recovers and the discomfort caused by back pain is avoided.</item>
        <item>Nombre:Dandruff# Descripcion:Dandruff is the not always excessive formation of flakes or crusts of dead skin formed on the scalp. # Remedies: Olive oil has been used since time immemorial and throughout the world to cure dandruff. The treatment is very easy, just rub the scalp with this oil and let it work overnight. Not only is dandruff completely eliminated and its return is prevented, but also vigorous and shiny hair is obtained. Beer being rich in vitamin B and having yeast, beer is very beneficial for the hair. Beer rinses are especially great for treating dandruff. You just have to wash your head every night with a bottle of this product. Like olive oil, in addition to curing dandruff, beer makes hair look shiny. Of course, do not wash before going outside, as the ethyl odor would be a bit embarrassing.% The vinegar-based remedy is one of the most effective in eliminating dandruff once and for all. It is about applying a cup of this product to the hair just when you finish washing the hair with your usual shampoo. It should not be rinsed with water, but left overnight. You will see that soon your worries will end.% The beet juice method is very simple. Take two or three beets and boil them in water until the liquid turns totally purple. Let cool and then apply to the scalp, rubbing gently. Perform the treatment every night for 2 or 3 weeks until you see that the dandruff disappears. Another excellent remedy for treating dandruff in hair is aloe vera. Apply its gel on the scalp and rub well. Leave the product on overnight. The next day wash the scalp in the usual way.% For lemon lovers this treatment is very positive. Just mix the juice of 2 lemons with a cup of warm water. Place your head over a sink and apply this remedy by vigorously rubbing the scalp and massaging. This cleanses the hair, frees it from dandruff and lice, and also gives it freshness and shine.% Boil orange peels (sweet or sour) when at room temperature, massage into the scalp, after washing the head.</item>
        <item>Nombre:Hair loss# Descripcion:Hair loss can be due to various factors such as stress, hormonal changes and even dyeing or the continued use of the dryer or curling irons. # Remedies: Green tea contains different antioxidants that stimulate hair growth and prevent hair loss. To use it as a natural remedy, you must prepare an infusion with two sachets for each cup of water and apply it hot to the scalp. Let it act for an hour and then wash it as you normally do. % Onion juice contains a large amount of sulfur. This prevents hair loss by improving blood circulation to the hair follicles. To use it, extract the juice from an onion and strain it. Apply it on the scalp leaving it to act for 30 minutes and then wash your hair as you normally do. You should repeat the treatment twice a week for two to three months. % Essential oils such as lavender, rosemary or thyme have been shown to help prevent hair loss. Massage any of them into your scalp after shampooing and you will see that your hair will gain much more strength. % Aloe Vera helps in the production of collagen and, therefore, helps to fix the hair strands to the scalp, preventing them from falling out. In addition to this, it has minerals and water, it strengthens the entire strand making it stronger and less brittle. Regular use of this plant prevents hair loss and relieves itching caused by dandruff. To use it, place aloe vera gel on your scalp and leave it to act for two hours and then rinse it with warm water. Repeat the process three or four times a week.% Beet or beet juice contains a series of vitamins and minerals that strengthen hair, preventing hair loss. You can also boil the leaves together with henna and make a paste that you will have to apply on your scalp, leaving it to act for about 20 minutes and then rinse. Repeat three times a week. %</item>
        <item>Nombre:Cystitis# Descripcion:Acute cystitis is an infection of the lower urinary tract, caused by bacteria (it can be staph, strep, or chlamydia). # Remedies: If you drink every day, fasting, a glass of water with two tablespoons of sodium bicarbonate you can prevent cystitis or reduce its discomfort. Although its taste is not very pleasant, it is a very effective remedy. Its properties prevent the bacteria that cause this infection from surviving on the walls of the urethra.% Radishes have an excellent property they are antibiotics. This means that its consumption (raw) helps fight infections. They are also dirutetic and, therefore, facilitate the expulsion of the invaders through the urine, thereby preventing them from remaining in the urinary tract. Spinach not only gives us strength and iron, but also provides us with a good amount of vitamins, minerals and antioxidants to face any disease. It is recommended to consume raw, in salads or in smoothies.% Parsley is another of the natural remedies recommended to complement the treatment of urinary infections. It helps to eliminate all toxins through the urine, and, in turn, strengthens the renal metabolism. To get the benefits of parsley, you simply have to boil a handful of leaves in two cups of water. Let stand, filter and drink throughout the day.% You can use the fluid extract of rosemary, about 20 drops in a tablespoon of water, 3 times a day. This magical plant, among other things, is also used for sexy urinary. Romerillo can also be mixed with red mangrove. An infusion is prepared with the bark of the red mangrove. Take a bunch of the latter and take a macere it in a container that contains a liter of water. Let it sit for at least 4-5 hours and drink 3 glasses a day.</item>
        <item>Nombre:High cholesterol# Descripcion:Keeping blood cholesterol levels properly balanced is important to ensure the proper functioning of the hormonal system and prevent cardiovascular diseases such as heart attacks.# Remedios:In the treatment to lower cholesterol, it is advisable to avoid eating foods of animal origin and also fatty foods such as red meat, butter, butter and oils of corn, sunflower, canola. Using fresh fruits and vegetables in the diet, and consuming cereals and whole-grain carbohydrates help the body eliminate excess fat from the blood, improving quality of life as well as health.% Avocado is rich in healthy fats and antioxidants that help lower bad cholesterol. Salvia leaves (4 or 5 leaves), boil it in ¼ liter of water over low heat until it becomes 1 cup of coffee; (1 time a day), preferably in the morning at least take it for 45 days.% the eggplant is cut into 7 pieces and each piece is passed through the blender along with the juice of 3 sweet oranges, this dose is taken daily and the treatment is applied for 7 days, rest 5 days and repeat the treatment for another 7 days, rest 5 more days and finally it is applied for 7 days, in total there are 21 doses for 31 days.</item>
        <item>Nombre:Diarrhea# Descripcion:Diarrhea is a way that the body has to defend itself against some microorganism that is in the digestive system, since through it the body seeks to eliminate it, so fighting diarrhea can make the harmful agent remain in the body during longer, making the infection worse. For this reason the use of antidiarrheal drugs should only be done after the second day of liquid stools. # Remedios:It is advisable to eat foods that are easily digestible and rich in water, in addition to increasing the consumption of liquids in general such as water, coconut water, juices or natural teas. % Chamomile has been used for centuries for its medicinal properties. Although the scientific evidence about its effectiveness is not yet conclusive, it is attributed antispasmodic and anti-inflammatory properties. You can prepare an infusion with pre-packaged tea bags, or buy the flowers and boil them. Drink chamomile tea several times a day, at least it will be a way to hydrate you. Diarrhea causes the elimination of vital minerals, salts and sugars for the organism, a homemade serum of water with bicarbonate will provide the necessary liquid and electrolytes that are lost with this stomach disease and will help to avoid dehydration.% Rice water is a classic. Rice water is believed to ease symptoms such as stomach pain and cramps. In addition, because it is rich in starch, it protects your body mucous membranes and reduces stomach irritation and stops diarrhea. Lemon water is credited with an astringent effect that prevents fluid loss from the intestine and helps to normalize the flow of acids through the digestive tract. Take the juice of 2 lemons in a liter of water, with a pinch of salt and bicarbonate to hydrate the body and recover lost minerals.% Boiled carrots provide water to combat dehydration; replenishes sodium, potassium, phosphorus, calcium, sulfur and magnesium, among other minerals and restores the balance of the intestinal flora.% It is not recommended to drink water with vinegar to prevent diarrhea, since vinegar is very astringent and there is a risk of getting sick with gastritis and even ulcerations, although this mixture contains diarrhea and is considered harmful to our health.</item>
        <item>Nombre:Muscle pain# Descripcion:Stress, poor posture, a sudden movement or weight bearing can damage muscles and eventually cause a contracture. It is a state of rigidity or contraction that the muscle suffers and that can be very painful. In addition, they can have a long recovery period that disrupts our rhythm of life.# Remedios:Valerian is one of the most used plants for stress cases. Its relaxing and antispasmodic activity can go well on the muscles and in this way help treat contractures. 300 to 900 mg of dry extract of the root are used, divided into 1 to 3 daily intakes. Do not take it in pregnancy.% For muscle inflammation, rosemary leaves can help. Rosemary contains anti-inflammatory properties that can soothe muscle tissues and help decrease pain. $ Ice is the quintessential remedy for runners and athletes, it works wonders when we want to reduce inflammation of any part of the body. But if you do not know this remedy, in case of severe muscle pain, apply ice to the affected area to relax the muscles and reduce inflammation. A great home remedy for treating muscle pain is pepper. Prepare a mixture of ground pepper and baby oil and massage the affected muscle area.%</item>
        <item>Nombre:Constipation# Descripcion:Constipation is a condition that consists of the lack of regular movement of the intestines, which produces infrequent or strained defecation, usually of scanty and hard stools.# Remedios:Aloe vera or aloe vera juice can help you have more frequent bowel movements. Of course, it doesn‘t always have an immediate effect. It is recommended to drink a glass of juice every day to help the digestive system move waste until it is expelled via the anal. % One of the best remedies for constipation is the apple. This fruit contains pectin; a substance that promotes intestinal function. In addition, it provides a significant amount of fiber, necessary to soften the stool and stimulate its expulsion. Banana is one of the fruits that help promote good digestion and improve bowel movement. It provides a good amount of fiber, which acts as a powerful natural laxative to facilitate the expulsion of stool. A piece of banana provides, on average, 12 percent of the recommended daily amount of fiber. In addition, it contains oligosaccharides, substances that, upon reaching the large intestine, contribute to good digestion.% People suffering from constipation should include more oats in their diet. This food contains carbohydrates, vitamins, minerals and fiber, which contribute to better digestion and avoid constipation. The ideal is to consume it for breakfast, but it can also be added to smoothies, soups and salads. Another remedy for constipation is to dilute 1 teaspoon of apple cider vinegar and 1 teaspoon of honey in a glass of water. Mix all the ingredients and drink this natural laxative three times a day. In a short time the intestinal transit will be much more regular.% The pump fruit also called papaya is rich in water and fiber, being well known for its ability to help intestinal function. It contains 1 g of fiber, around 11 g of carbohydrate and 40 kcal per 100 g, in addition to nutrients such as magnesium, potassium and vitamin C.% The plum, both in the fresh version and in the dehydrated form, is rich in fiber and is a good food for the intestine. Each unit of black plum has about 1.2 g of fibers, in addition to providing phosphorus, potassium and B vitamins for the body.</item>
        <item> Nombre:Stretch marks# Descripcion:Stretch marks are marks caused by stretching of the skin. The elastic fibers located under the surface of the skin break and are seen with the naked eye. Once they appear, it is not possible to completely eliminate stretch marks as the skin is damaged, although they can be reduced or made less noticeable. Therefore it is best to avoid or prevent them.# Remedios:Lemon juice is reputed to be very good for treating skin problems. Lemon acid can help reduce scars, blemishes, or marks caused by stretch marks, acne, or wounds. Cocoa butter is an exceptional natural moisturizer that can also help promote circulation and delay aging.% A very easy home remedy to reduce stretch marks is with coconut oil. Put one to two teaspoons of coconut oil in a bowl. Put the container in a water bath until the oil is hot. Making sure that the oil is not too hot to burn the skin, apply it with a massage on the parts where you have the problem of stretch marks or where you want to prevent them. Another easy way to remove stretch marks is with flaxseed oil. Due to its high content of vitamin E, flaxseed oil promotes cell regeneration and can help reduce the appearance of stretch marks. </item>
        <item>Nombre:Fever# Descripcion:Fever is not a disease, but a defense mechanism of the body and, therefore, it is related to the stimulation of the immune system, which causes an increase in body temperature to more than 38ºC. When a person has a body temperature between 37ºC and 38ºC, they are said to have a low-grade fever, that is, a mild or mild fever.# Remedios:Cold water has always been used to lower fever. It is common for many people to place cloths soaked in cold water on the forehead or the back of the neck. But you can also wet a sponge with cold water and moisten the areas of the armpits, feet, hands and groin. It is a good remedy when the fever is very high.% Another widely used natural remedy is a warm water bath, as it helps to relax the body. It is not advisable to shower when a person has a fever and discomfort, since in these cases it is better for the person to be relaxed and in a resting position.% Drinking a lot of water and frequently is good to fight fever, since the body suffers from dehydration when it fights against external agents. Drinking water is especially important when the person also has diarrhea or vomits. Hot garlic can help lower body temperature by promoting sweating. In this sense, it helps eliminate toxins and promotes recovery. This food has an antibacterial and antifungal effect, so it becomes a great ally of the body to fight infections. Another infusion that goes very well when we have a fever is sage tea, which helps perspire and lowers fever. This drink is easy to prepare. You just have to place a few sage leaves in a cup of boiling water and let them rest for 10 minutes. Honey and lemon juice can be added to increase its benefits.% Thanks to ginger, the body releases heat and therefore reduces fever. This substance is a natural antiviral and benefits the immune system. Ginger can be drunk in an infusion or it is possible to make a bath with ginger powder. When the bathtub is full, simply add the ginger powder and oil and let it work for 10 minutes before taking a 10-minute bath.% Egg white, although many are unaware of it, also helps lower fever. Due to its viscosity, it acts as a cool gel that absorbs heat. Apparently, if a paper cloth is dipped in previously beaten egg whites and placed on the feet (with the sock on top so that it stays in place), it acts as a layer of fat that absorbs body heat and reduces the fever. % Slice an onion and place it on the ground. Step on it with bare feet so that the juice penetrates the body. Stay as long as you can in this position. If the treatment is carried out on young children, the onions can be put into the socks. This is another very effective homemade recipe, especially for the little ones: cut a potato into slices and place it on the soles of the feet. Tie it up with a handkerchief or socks and let it act.</item>
        <item>Nombre:Gastritis# Descripcion:Gastritis is a problem in which the stomach lining becomes swollen or inflamed and can be caused by taking certain drugs, drinking alcohol, or by a stomach infection. # Remedios:One of the ways is to prepare teas or juices with the fresh ginger. But also, in cases of gastritis, you can bring greater relief if you mix a piece of fresh ginger with 2 carrots, 4 stalks of celery and half an apple. It is effective in stopping nausea in the first 3 months of pregnancy. When you drink warm water with lemon, the stomach receives the signal that the acidity increased and stops producing the gastric juices that cause heartburn and stomach pain. In addition, lemon is healing, so it can heal local ulcers. Take a bunch of parsley and place in a blender with 1 glass of water, blend and then drink several times a day; the symptoms will gradually decrease. Parsley has potassium, calcium and phosphorus, it is also considered a very good diuretic and effective for the relief of other stomach ailments.% Blend the cabbage with a small amount of water and strain and drink 2 or 3 cups of this juice daily, half an hour before meals or when symptoms appear. Drinking this juice regularly will cure gastritis. You can also eat shredded cabbage in salads for more benefits. Chamomile is boiled in a small 10 to 12 ounce jug of water. When it is boiling, add a handful of chamomile leaves and flowers. It is removed from the heat and the container is covered. After two or three hours, it is strained and you can have a cup one in the morning, another in the afternoon and the last one before meals. This remedy can be a good incentive, but always remember to consult your doctor if you suffer from chronic gastritis.</item>
        <item>Nombre:Halitosis# Descripcion:Halitosis is a clinical sign characterized by bad breath or unpleasant mouth odor. It is usually caused by bacteria# Remedios:The first brushing of the day, with baking soda. The antimicrobial properties of this compound make it a perfect ally to fight bad breath, as it helps to eliminate the bacteria that cause odor.% Chew parsley after each brushing. Although it does not sound like the most appealing home remedy, the truth is that the chlorophyll of this plant manages to neutralize halitosis if, before each brushing, it is chewed mixed with a few drops of vinegar. % Lemon juice rinses first thing in the morning. The citric acid in this winter fruit stops the proliferation of bacteria on the tongue and gums. Therefore, rinsing your mouth and gargling every day and after each brushing with a glass of lemon juice and warm water helps to keep your breath fresh throughout the day, no matter what you eat. %</item>
        <item>Nombre:Herpes# Descripcion:Herpes is a viral infectious inflammatory disease characterized by the appearance of skin lesions formed by small vesicles grouped in clusters and surrounded by a red ring.# Remedios:Propolis extract is an excellent natural remedy that helps wound healing, as it has antiviral and regenerative properties, which will reduce the duration of herpes and facilitate skin healing. To help herpes wounds heal, just apply 3 to 4 drops of propolis extract 3 times a day on them.% Black tea bags can be applied to areas with herpes 2 to 3 times a day, helping to relieve pain, discomfort, and itching caused by the disease. Gauze or cotton pieces can be soaked in Calendula Flower tea, 3 times a day, applying it for about 10 minutes. This tea will help reduce the discomfort and itching caused by herpes. Garlic is a food that works as a natural antibiotic and to use it to treat herpes wounds, just cut a tooth in half and rub it directly on the wounds or blisters, or you can prepare a small paste to apply to the skin. A bunch of Plantain, boil it in 1 liter of water and put it in compresses 3 times a day on the affected part.</item>
        <item>Nombre:Liver# Descripcion:To cleanse the liver there are recipes that are a supplement to food. It is very important to bear in mind that they do not act on their own, since in general eating habits must be improved.# Remedios:Thanks to their antioxidant properties, grapefruit, lemon and orange juice are the favorites to eliminate toxins and fats from our entire body, in addition to helping the colon and liver. They also strengthen the immune system and promote good health. This game is recommended to be taken in the morning and always fresh. If you think it is too acidic you can add some green vegetables. Beetroot is rich in antioxidants thanks to the fact that it contains betalines, which is the substance that gives it its characteristic purple color. It favors the elimination of heavy metals from our body and, consequently, helps to cleanse the liver. % Orange and ginger juice fight infection and dissolve stones. This juice combines the antioxidant benefits of orange with the properties of ginger. The latter helps improve everything related to digestion and has anti-inflammatory qualities. The result will be a refreshing juice that cleanses the liver without remorse. It is advisable to drink this juice 3 nights in a row. However, if you want to see older, effects you can take it for 7 nights. Grapefruit is an excellent fruit to eliminate toxins and a great ally for liver health. Combined with the benefits of ginger and garlic, we can obtain a juice that is perfect to stimulate detoxification.</item>
        <item>Nombre:Urinary infection# Descripcion:Urinary infection is the existence of pathogenic germs in the urine due to infection of the urethra, bladder, kidney or prostate.# Remedios:Blueberries are an excellent option to treat urinary tract infection in pregnancy, since blueberries have a high concentration of proanthocyanidins that make it difficult for Escherichia Coli bacteria to adhere to the walls of the urinary tract, reducing the possibility of contracting the disease. % This enzyme present in pineapple has been proven to have properties that benefit the urinary tract of patients. From the success of this study, it is recommended within a balanced diet, eat a cup of pineapple daily to maintain a healthy urinary system. In some cases, not only antibiotics are prescribed, but also vitamin C to help fight urinary tract infection, since it contains antioxidants that boost the immune system. It is advisable to increase the intake of fruits that contain a high amount of this vitamin during the treatment, to achieve a quick improvement.% Hydration is essential for good health. In the event that a person has a urinary tract infection, they should take even more care of their water intake, since by urinating they will be able to expel pathogens from their system. In relation to diseases of the urinary bladder and prostatitis, it is recommended to drink juice of any type of orange, several times a day, this stimulates the functions of the urinary bladder and deflates the prostate gland.</item>
        <item>Nombre:Insomnia# Descripcion:Insomnia is one of the most common sleep disorders that consists of the difficulty in initiating sleep# Remedios:Drinking a cup of warm milk with honey and a pinch of cinnamon powder, is that advice from grandmother that many of us carry out, almost to the letter. It is a simple method that basically helps you relax thanks to the disconnection moment that a warm drink provides before going to sleep. Milk is also a source of tryptophan, an amino acid that is involved in the formation of serotonin, which in turn regulates melatonin, known as the sleep hormone. Valerian is scientifically proven to improve sleep and relax and relieve nerves. Many of the insomnia remedies sold at the drugstore contain valerian. Valerian can also be taken as an infusion that can be bought or prepared at home. Now, valerian as an infusion is usually found combined with other herbs, since by itself its flavor is not very pleasant. Or it comes in valerian pills, which contains plant root extract. The chamomile infusion has many properties, muscle relaxation, helps digestion. . . If you want to make your own chamomile infusion, you can use the dried chamomile flowers with boiling water and that‘s it. And if you want you can add a little honey or squeeze a little lemon. All of these options are great home remedies for getting a good night‘s sleep. and you have to find out the cause of sleep problems. In addition, if the situation lasts longer, we must carry out a series of changes in our habits. For nervous disorders, sweating and insomnia, an infusion is prepared with leaves of the orange bush, put to a boil and when it begins to boil, it is removed from the heat and 5 grams of crushed leaves are added in small portions, the container is covered. and leave it to rest for 30 minutes, sweeten it and after straining it, take a cup when you consider it necessary.% Take 1 or 2 teaspoons of Bee Honey at bedtime.% Look for 4 to 5 sour orange leaves, a sprig of yerba buena, the juice of half a lemon and sugar to taste. All this is boiled in a medium jug with half a liter of water. After it cools down, strain it and drink it before going to bed.</item>
        <item>Nombre:Spots on the face# Descripcion:We all want to have blemish-free porcelain skin, but as time goes by we realize that with the sun and stress, it is more common every day to find small pigmentations along the face.# Remedios:Apply plain yogurt on the stains and top with some carrot slices. Leave them for a few minutes and rinse. Mix five tablespoons of blended cucumber, five tablespoons of crushed parsley, five tablespoons of sesame or wheat germ oil in a glass jar, close it tightly and place it in a dark place for a few days. Apply in compresses on the stains for 20 minutes and then wash it off. Boil the yucca until it softens and make a puree, then apply on the face. Mix a lemon, two tablespoons of milk and aloe vera pulp. Squeeze the lemon and mix it with the milk, apply it to the affected area and after it dries, put the aloe vera pulp and cover with gauze. Leave it as long as possible and remove with water.% Apply lemon every night before going to bed and wash your face when you wake up. It is one of the best known remedies but you must be very careful not to expose yourself to the sun because you would stain more. Crush an onion and mix it with a little vinegar, apply directly to the stain, leave it on for 15 minutes and rinse. It is important not to expose yourself to the sun afterwards. Mix a tablespoon of tomato juice with a tablespoon of lemon juice, apply with a cotton ball on the stains and leave for 20 minutes. Rinse.% Mix an egg yolk with natural yogurt and half a tablespoon of honey, spread it on the skin and leave for 30 minutes. Rinse with lukewarm water.% Crush a banana and add the juice of a lemon, apply the mixture on the skin and let it rest for 20 minutes. Rinse.% Use the peels of the bomba fruit or papaya and rub the affected skin with the inside. Helps remove blemishes and regenerates the skin.% Mix two tablespoons of milk with the juice of a lemon, apply with cotton wool and wait for it to dry. Then apply a little Aloe Vera. Remember not to expose yourself to the sun after applying this remedy.% Grind a little root and mix it with lemon juice, apply with cotton wool on the stains and remove with warm water</item>
        <item>Nombre:Menopause# Descripcion:Menopause is defined as the permanent cessation of menstruation and has physiological correlations. It is a very important stage of changes for women that usually causes different symptoms, such as hot flashes, sweats, dryness, overweight, instability in mood. However, each woman experiences it differently and with greater or lesser intensity.# Remedios:In addition to some very beneficial supplements for a healthy and happy menopause, a balanced diet is always the key to maintaining health. To improve health in general and prevent the symptoms of menopause we can benefit from all the properties of garlic, a medicinal food that purifies the body and improves circulation. We can consume raw garlic by spreading it on toast or adding it to homemade vegetable juices. Legumes are a very beneficial food in menopause for two reasons. On the one hand, they are rich in vegetable protein and fiber, so that they improve intestinal function and help reduce the fat that accumulates around the waist. On the other hand, they are rich in phytoestrogens or estrogens of plant origin, which help regulate the hormonal imbalances that are suffered at this stage and cause the annoying symptoms.</item>
        <item> Nombre:Memory# Descripcion:Forgetfulness is one of the main concerns of people approaching their old age.# Remedios:Insufficient intake of vitamins can result in the appearance of forgetfulness. Include in your diet foods that are rich in thiamine, such as pistachios, sunflower seeds, and asparagus. Vitamin E is also essential for maintaining a healthy brain. Including spinach, avocado, etc., it helps you maintain your memory capacity.% Drinks like tea are a great source of antioxidants and make it easy to access the memory bank. So next time you go shopping, don‘t forget to add a packet of herbal tea. Carotene is an important element for the nutrition of a healthy brain. Carrots are a rich source of carotene, therefore an effective home remedy for memory loss. Include carrots in your diet to see how it works wonders on your memory. Eat them raw or cooked, for a sharp mind that refuses to forget. Nuts like almonds, apricots, macadamia nuts and walnut are correctly called brain foods. The natural oils in these nuts contain anti-inflammatory properties and protective nutrients that help keep the brain in good shape. So next time you feel the urge to binge eat, go ahead and dive into a handful of nuts. They are the wonderful home remedies for memory capacity. If you are not a vegetarian, you have an excellent source of memory booster at your disposal. Fish like salmon, sardines, mackerel, and anchovies are packed with healthy fats known as omega-3 fatty acids. Omega-3 fatty acids that are anti-inflammatory agents have incredible health benefits. They help keep the brain healthy and active, by preventing cell / nerve degeneration. </item>
        <item>Nombre:Migraine# Descripcion:Migraine is a disease whose main symptom is a headache, usually very intense and disabling for those who suffer from it. Along with the pain, other discomforts may appear, such as feeling dizzy, sensitivity to light, and nausea and vomiting. Fortunately, they disappear in a matter of hours and rarely indicate a more serious problem.# Remedios:Due to its content of an active compound called gingerol, ginger serves as a remedy to combat migraine headaches and headaches. This substance acts as an anti-inflammatory and analgesic, reducing the tension in the head. Thanks to its relaxing effect, the chamomile infusion also helps reduce those headache attacks. Drink 2 or 3 cups of infusion a day. The infusion is prepared by previously boiling 200 milliliters of water in a container. When the boiling begins, remove the container from the heat, add a handful of chamomile flowers and leaves, cover it and leave it to rest for 60 minutes. After filtering or straining with an antiseptic cloth or gauze, the ingestion of the doses already indicated begins.% The lemongrass infusion has properties that help fight oxidative stress and minimize the recurrence of headaches. It also favors the reactivation of blood circulation and, due to this, contributes to the treatment of migraine.% The delicate scent of roses is a natural relaxant that fights stress, anxiety and nerves. Therefore, a few steams with rose water can minimize the tension that is produced by migraines and headaches. The fatty acids in olive oil have an anti-inflammatory effect that helps curb headaches. In fact, its regular consumption is recommended as a preventive against migraine. Peppermint‘s analgesic properties help fight migraines and headaches. Of course, it is not as strong as conventional medications, so several doses a day are required to feel relief.</item>
        <item>Nombre:Eyecup# Descripcion:It is the alteration of the color of the skin located under the eyes due to an excessive production of melanin and the dilation of the capillaries near the skin‘s surface.# Remedios:A very effective trick is to soak some cotton pads in the chamomile infusion and apply it to closed eyes overnight. Cucumber is used to reduce puffiness in the eye area. It is recommended to apply fresh cucumber slices on the eyes for a few minutes to take effect. Aloe vera is known for its healing properties and greatly reduces dark circles. Simply apply a little product to the area and let it act for a few minutes.</item>
        <item>Nombre:Stye# Descripcion:A stye is an inflammation of a gland at the base of the eyelashes.# Remedios:Warm stye compresses help relieve pain, inflammation, and drain pus from inside the stye, if it is infected. Wash your eyes 2 to 3 times a day with an infusion of chamomile and rosemary, which calms, relieves pain and discomfort. Rosemary is added as it has antibacterial properties, helping to treat the infection, in case the stye has pus. % Aloe vera or also called aloe, is a medicinal plant that has antibacterial and anti-inflammatory properties, being able to reduce the inflammation of the stye and prevent infection with bacteria. This medicine can be used before washing the eye to relieve redness, pain, and swelling.% One of the most important care in the treatment of a stye is to keep the eye well washed, to avoid an infection that can increase inflammation. So baby shampoo is a great option to wash the eye, since it is able to leave the skin well washed without burning or irritating the eye. After washing, a warm compress can be applied to the eye to relieve discomfort.</item>
        <item>Nombre:High blood pressure, hypertension# Descripcion:Hypertension (HT) is a chronic disease characterized by a continuous increase in blood pressure levels in the arteries. # Remedios:Garlic water is an excellent way to regulate blood pressure because it stimulates the production of nitric oxide, which is a gas with a strong vasodilator action, which facilitates blood circulation and reduces pressure on the heart. % A good home remedy to control high blood pressure is to drink a lemonade mixed with coconut water because this juice has diuretic properties that help regulate blood pressure. Several Bomba Fruit Leaves, boil it for 10 or 15 minutes, strain it and take this decoction 1 glass at night and another glass in the morning, for several days, until it is controlled, repeat as many times as necessary.</item>
        <item>Nombre:Hypotension, Low blood pressure# Descripcion:Hypotension refers to an abnormal condition in which a person‘s blood pressure is much lower than usual.# Remedios:Rosemary stimulates the central nervous system and improves blood circulation, calming vertigo and weakness. It is ideal that you massage your legs with drops of rosemary essential oil mixed with almond and olive oil. It can also be effective to drink a rosemary and honey tea, which will help oxygenation of cells and tissues. Take it at the first sign of low blood pressure. Coconut water with lemon restores electrolytes in the body and keeps blood pressure at healthy levels. Its essential minerals improve the passage of blood through the veins. You can have this drink in the middle of the morning or whenever you feel a drop in blood pressure. Ginger stimulates circulation, prevents blood from clotting, and increases body temperature. % Water with lemon, salt and sugar is very effective when there is dehydration. The properties of its ingredients help to recover energy, improve circulation and the functioning of the nervous system.% Some foods that can help you are bread, pasta, rice, potatoes, whole grains, vegetables, fish, lean chicken, and fruits. % You should avoid very abrupt changes in posture, increase your salt intake a little and sleep with your head up.</item>
        <item>Nombre:Burns# Descripcion:A burn is a type of injury to the skin caused by various factors. Thermal burns are caused by contact with flames, hot liquids, hot surfaces and other sources of high temperatures; even with contact with elements at extremely low temperatures. There are also chemical burns and electrical burns.# Remedios:Aloe Vera, probably the best-known home remedy for burns, stops pain and redness, reduces inflammation, and encourages skin growth and repair. But if you don‘t have aloe on hand, any cream or product that contains it will help you soothe the burned area. For when you accidentally touch something hot without a shield, or get splashed with boiling liquid, keep a tube of toothpaste in the kitchen (preferably white) to use as a home remedy for a minor burn. First, leave the area under a stream of cold water; then dry it very gently with a paper towel, and finish by covering it with a light layer of toothpaste. For minor burns, you can use vanilla extract. Use a cotton swab and dip it in the vanilla extract; then rub it very gently over the burned skin. The evaporation of the alcohol from the vanilla extract will cool the burn and relieve pain. Black tea contains tannic acid, which draws heat from burns to help reduce pain. (That same calming compound makes black tea a great home remedy for toothaches and many other pains.) Place two or three cold, wet black tea bags on the burned area, and secure them with gauze. White vinegar contains acetic acid, a component that you can also find in aspirin and that helps relieve pain, itching, and inflammation from a burn. It is also a natural antiseptic and astringent, so it will help keep the injury safe from infection. The vinegar also draws the heat out of the burn, helping to relieve pain naturally. Soak a few paper towels in diluted vinegar to create a soothing compress, or use cotton swabs to gently massage the injured area. Honey is a natural antibiotic that helps prevent infection from burns. It has a slightly acidic pH that is hostile to bacteria, so once applied to the skin it can also kill any germs present or cure stubborn infections. The honey will also cool the burn, relieving pain and helping it heal. The fat and protein content of milk soothes and promotes the healing of burns. Soak the burn in milk for 15 minutes for quick relief. Another option is to spread a little yogurt, since the fat it contains helps to hydrate dry skin. Coconut oil is an excellent source of vitamin E and also contains fatty acids that fight fungi and bacteria, thus helping to keep the burn protected from infection. If a burn has left a visible scar, mix the juice of a lemon with coconut oil and massage the mark. The acidity of the lemon juice will help to fade the scar, and the coconut oil to heal the skin. Ice can restrict blood flow to the skin and further aggravate the damage. Instead, immediately place the burned area under cool running water, which helps prevent the injury from spreading, and try to keep the affected area under water for at least 5 minutes if possible.</item>
        <item>Nombre:Rheumatism# Descripcion:It is known as a series of ailments of nonspecific origin. It is used to name certain pains that affect bones, joints, muscles, tendons and ligaments.# Remedios:Chronic inflammation plays an important role in the development of rheumatic diseases. Celery contains antioxidants that help reduce inflammation.% The potato or potato to contain so many minerals, it turns out to give an anti-inflammatory effect for the body. It is a popular remedy for rheumatism that has been applied for many years and is effective in both preventing and treating rheumatism. Prepare a decoction or decoction with 15 or 20 avocado leaves (green or purple). These leaves are poured into a container that contains one liter of water. It is brought to a simmer for 8 to 10 minutes. After that, it is strained with gauze or antiseptic cloth and packaged in a glass bottle, preferably an amber one. It is stored in the cold and at least three glasses are taken a day: morning, afternoon and night. It is noted that pregnant or pregnant women should not ingest this decoction as it has abortifacient properties.</item>
        <item>Nombre:Sinusitis# Descripcion:Sinusitis is an inflammatory response of the mucosa of the nose that can be due to an infection by bacterial, viral or fungal agents; or an allergic picture; or a combination of these factors. It is characterized by a runny nose, nasal obstruction, and facial pain. Symptoms include headache, cough, or fever.# Remedios:An excellent home remedy for sinusitis is to clean the nose and sinuses with a mixture of warm water and salt, as it helps to eliminate excess secretions and reduces inflammation, relieving symptoms such as pain and pressure at the level of the face. % For acute sinusitis, a remedy is to inhale the eucalyptus vapor because it has expectorant and antiseptic properties, quickly relieving nasal congestion. A home remedy for allergic sinusitis can be spinach juice with mint, as it contains anti-inflammatory and decongestant properties that help eliminate secretions, relieving the symptoms of sinusitis. If you have sinusitis, you should try not to travel by plane, avoid very hot or very cold temperatures or sudden changes in temperature, lean forward with your head down. If you have an allergy, and it is not well controlled, they can make sinusitis more difficult to treat.</item>
        <item>Nombre:Varicose veins# Descripcion:Varicose veins are venous dilations characterized by the inability to establish an effective return of blood to the heart (Venous insufficiency). The most common are from the lower extremity.# Remedios:The mixture of six finely chopped garlic cloves, with olive oil and lemon juice, rested for 12 hours, is applied on the legs giving light massages.% Chamomile tea with two tablespoons of apple cider vinegar is applied to varicose veins with a cotton ball in the morning and at night. The oil blend is effective for almost all types of pain. For this, the ideal is to mix two tablespoons of almond oil and cod liver oil, to later apply it with gentle massages and let it rest for an hour before rinsing.% To two liters of hot water add a handful of chamomile, one of mint and one of bay leaf. Let it sit for a bit and then add a teaspoon of baking soda. Apply the infusion on varicose veins every time you bathe.%</item>
        <item>Nombre:Vomit# Descripcion:Vomiting and nausea consists of a feeling of stomach discomfort that can spread throughout the cavity or be accentuated only in the mouth and include gas, punctures, burning and retching among other symptoms.# Remedios:To recover the minerals lost during vomiting, it is recommended to take serum; can be created quickly. It is only necessary to put a little salt, sugar and bicarbonate in a glass of water for later if you want to add a little lemon.% Sucking on some ice can help you avoid the urge to vomit. It is advisable to suck on the ice for a period of 3 minutes and if the urge to vomit returns, do it again. Compresses and water when we have vomit, it is recommended to wet a series of compresses with cold water and warm water, placing them in the belly area and interspersing, a couple of minutes with warm water and then a couple of minutes with cold water; in this way, the urge to vomit is reduced. Carrot and potato helps fight gastroenteritis, rehydrates, prevents gastric disorders and is easy to digest. Go through a blender a little water with a carrot and two washed and peeled potatoes. Drink this juice twice a day.% The properties of ginger are many, one of which is that it will help you fight gastroenteritis and reduce nausea. If green anise is added, its effects are enhanced thanks to its carminative properties that help restore proper functioning in the stomach. Drink an infusion of ginger and green anise twice a day and you will feel better.</item>
        <item>Nombre:Otitis# Descripcion:Otitis is inflammation of the ear generally due to an infectious cause. # Remedios:Traditionally many people prepare in a pan a kind of juice-juice with one or two leaves of the everlasting plant, also known as immortal or prodigious, the juice is extracted and put in the pan with a little oil to eat, after which it is warm, with a dropper it is poured into the ear where the condition exists, this same process is carried out with the juice of the oregano leaves.</item>
        <item>Nombre:Bursitis # Descripcion:Bursitis is an inflammation of one of the bursae, which are cavities filled with a lubricating fluid, the synovium, located especially in areas where there is friction or in places where muscles or tendons pass over bony areas. The most commonly affected joints are the shoulder, elbow, and hip, often referred to as frozen, due to loss of normal mobility.# Remedios:It is necessary to eat foods high in magnesium, vegetables with green leaves, and many green and yellow vegetables, you have to put boiled and filtered water, and take honey when you get up and before going to bed. It is recommended to take a tablespoon of cod liver oil, once or twice before each meal. % When severe pain appears, it is also recommended to take a strong infusion of chamomile. The mode of preparation consists of boiling the water, pouring a good bunch of chamomile flowers and having a cup before going to bed, it is proposed to prepare ice compresses and place one above and one below the joint affected by bursitis, maintaining it for 20 minutes. 3 times a day.% From the point of view of juice therapy, there are those who recommend a dose of equal parts of carrot, celery, cucumber and beet juice, to face cases of this disease. % Another variant is a decoction with 20 avocado leaves and put them in a container with a liter of water and take 3 glasses a day.</item>
        <item>Nombre:Pinworms# Descripcion:It is one of the most common intestinal parasites. 80% of children between 2 and 10 years of age get pinworms at some point. # Remedios:Place two cloves of garlic in a liter of water, boil for a few minutes, cool and place in a bag for an enema, put on a chair and ask the child to lie face down on the chair with his legs hanging, the anal opening is lubricated and the enema tube is slid in about 2 cm, this helps to eliminate pinworms. % There is a way of using the same previous process but with a decoction of bunches of cundiamor.</item>
        <item>Nombre:Scabies# Descripcion:It is known, it is a contagious disease caused by the infestation of the skin, by the Sarcoptes scabiei mite, a hominis variety that can appear at any stage of life, in different social strata, although it is more frequent where overcrowding predominates, and when hygienic practices are rare.# Remedios:Sulfur is highly recommended for being very effective in eliminating the mites of this disease due to its great toxicity. The same, you can apply it directly on the skin, bathing with sulfur-based soap, or a part in ten of cream and with petroleum jelly, being the safest in pregnant or lactating women. Neem oil and leaves are a wonder of nature for various skin conditions and scoria is no exception. The oil is extracted from the fruits or you can buy it in herbalists, stores. Apply the same in the area daily and for two weeks.% Take a shower with vinegar and warm water or apply by compresses or directly to the affected area to destroy the presence of mites.% Add half a cup of baking soda to your bathtub and sit in it for 15 minutes. Also, prepare a paste with 1 part of water with 3 of sodium bicarbonate.% One of the most important natural plants with its antibacterial properties and very ideal for attacking fungi, parasites or bacteria. Extract the gel from the aloe leaf with a spoon, then apply it directly to the affected skin for a while to make it adsorb. You can repeat this procedure twice a day and for two weeks. Onion with antibiotic properties such as aloe, effective to combat these parasites because it contains sulfur. You can rub it on the affected part or heat several and apply the water in compresses or bath.% An excellent home remedy for scabies is to massage the affected region with olive oil, as it helps soothe and hydrate the skin, relieving the itchiness that scabies causes and that worsens when the person scratches. Heat the olive oil and when it is warm, place it on a gauze or cotton ball and massage the affected region several times a day. The application of olive oil should be avoided in the regions where the skin has a wound.% Watercress is a plant that has a strong purifying action, which is why it is capable of eliminating toxins accumulated in the blood, reducing skin inflammation and itching caused by scabies. In addition to this, watercress is rich in vitamin A, a micronutrient that helps maintain skin health. Place 2 bouquets of watercress and 200 ml of water in the blender and blend until a homogeneous mixture is obtained. Drink 1 glass of this juice every day on an empty stomach.% Rue is a medicinal plant that is widely used as a home remedy for skin problems due to its soothing properties that combat skin irritation. In this form it is an excellent remedy to quickly relieve the itching caused by scabies. Place 20 g of rue in a pot and add 1 liter of water to it and boil for 5 minutes. Strain the mixture and dip the clean compresses in the water. Remove excess liquid from the compresses and apply to the affected regions.% Taking a bath with chamomile tea is also an excellent option because this medicinal plant has soothing properties, being widely used to treat skin irritations, including in cases of chickenpox. Place the chamomile leaves in the water and boil in 1 liter of water. Strain, let cool and bathe with slightly cold water and the tea all over the body. In summary, the recommendations for its prevention are to pat the area and avoid scratching, use cold or warm water, bathe periodically, use antibacterial soap, not have intimate contact with anyone, avoid sharing clothes with infected people, wash all clothes or isolate it in a bag , personal hygiene, ventilate the entire home and treat all family members whether or not they have symptoms.</item>
        <item> Nombre:Pediculosis, Lice# Descripcion:Pediculosis is a skin condition caused by infestation by a louse, it is located mainly on the scalp.# Remedios:Rosemary is an aromatic plant that, due to its vitamin and mineral content, provides many benefits for the health of our hair, helps to strengthen hair, stops hair loss and helps keep it free of pests such as lice. It works as a lice repellent due to the unbearable smell (for them). To prepare it, we will put a handful of rosemary leaves in water, letting it boil for 5 minutes. When it has rested and is warm, we will have a perfumed water to wet the hair of the patient before combing it.% The natural fatty acids in coconut oil are toxic to lice. When we apply coconut oil to our hair, due to the oleic substances present in its composition, lice and nits cannot catch on, they cannot stay attached to the hair. In this way we can end them and cut their cycle. % Due to its sulfur compounds, garlic is considered to be a remedy that alters the adequate environment for the survival of lice and, if we combine it with lemon, we obtain an ideal mixture to eliminate lice and nits. We will use three or four cloves of garlic, depending on the length of the hair, and a few drops of lemon juice. Then we grind this mixture until we obtain a paste. We apply the paste by massaging the hair and cover the head with a hat. We let it work overnight. In the morning we should rinse the hair with hot water and wash it regularly. Then we will comb the hair with the lendrera. We must repeat this process weekly until we are able to completely eliminate lice and nits. It fragments the red mamey seed to extract a kind of almond, and crush it to the maximum to convert it into a substance that is mixed with alcohol, that is, the mamey almond is poured into a small container containing alcohol, left to rest for one hour, and an alcoholic maceration comes out. Thereafter, it is smeared on the head, and it is covered with a cloth for 30 minutes, then a very fine comb is passed, and the head is washed. This operation is carried out for three consecutive days, and is repeated again after seven days. It is a surefire remedy for pediculosis capitis, not only for nits but also for adult lice. </item>
        <item>Nombre:Low back pain or lumbago# Descripcion:A common pain disorder affecting the lower spine which can be caused by an injury to a muscle or ligament.# Remedios:A remedy can be a hot bath with sulfur. Immersion in hot water is one of the most effective non-pharmacological pain relief methods, and it is used as a relaxant and analgesic on a regular basis in many pathologies (hydrotherapy). Buy sulfur powder from a reputable herbalist and add 100 g to the bath water. Immerse yourself and let the hot water and mineral act. Regarding its cutaneous use, it is worth noting rosemary oil, essential in injuries. It is a preparation that helps us reduce the swelling of the affected area due to its anti-inflammatory power. It is a muscle relaxant that together with thyme and sage cause a pleasant sensation in the painful area. It is important that they are applied by giving a light massage to enhance their effects. St. John‘s wort and mint applied to the lesion help to relax the area and reduce pain. Ginger oil works in a way similar to an NSAID (non-steroidal anti-inflammatory) but naturally. It is relaxing, anti-inflammatory and analgesic. To prepare this remedy, mix 5 drops of essential oil with 10 of sweet almond oil and apply it to the painful area with a gentle massage. Consuming pineapple will help us reduce swelling and accelerate recovery, since pineapple bromeliad is a substance that has anti-inflammatory effects. This substance can be found in papaya. Of course, they must be natural and in the case of pineapple we have to eat the heart, as it contains more amounts of nutrients.</item>
        <item>Nombre:Vitiligo# Descripcion:It is a degenerative disease of the skin, and is manifested by the appearance of white spots that result from the absence of pigment in the skin.# Remedios:Find a red mamey or mamey sapote seed and extract what is known as the almond that is inside it. It is conveniently crushed and brought to a boil in a medium jug. After it boils, a tablespoon of lard is added and it is ready to spread that substance on places on the body where vitiligo appears. % Apply Vimang ointment twice a day, which is a powerful natural antioxidant that acts topically on various skin conditions.</item>
        <item>Nombre:Psoriasis# Descripcion: It is a chronic inflammatory disease of the skin that produces thickened and inflamed squamous lesions, with a wide clinical and evolutionary variability. It is not contagious, although it can be inherited, it is more likely to be inherited by men than women.# Remedios:Cooking with leaves and stem of French Macaw, is applied in the mornings, preferably in places near the coast or the sea and after it is applied in the affected places, let it dry by itself, when it is dry, then apply shark liver oil. This is done daily for 60 days.% Make a decoction or decoction of the Sarsaparilla leaves, take a cup or at most 2 cups a day. It cannot be taken during the time that the cooking, Alcoholic Beverages, or Stimulants are taken.%</item>
        <item>Nombre:Hemorrhoids# Descripcion:They are varicose veins or inflammation of the veins in the rectum and anus. They are the result of straining to evacuate the intestines, although they can be caused by other factors such as pregnancy, chronic constipation, diarrhea or aging.# Remedios:Prepare a decoction or decoction with a good bunch of leaves, stems and bark from the trunk or thick branches of the Almendra bush or the tree known as Almendro. That bunch is poured into a container containing three or four liters of water and simmered for 8 to 10 minutes. After straining or filtering this decoction, sitz baths are carried out twice a day. The water should be warm or somewhat hot. For cases of non-painful hemorrhoids, the water will be cold or at room temperature.% Simultaneously with the previous remedy before sleeping, frozen ovules or suppositories are applied with the pulp or crystal of the aloe leaf.</item>
        <item>Nombre:Tonsillitis# Descripcion: It is the inflammation of a palatine tonsil or both, caused mainly by a virus.# Remedios:Add to a medium jug of water 4 or 5 sage leaves, they are fragmented and placed on the fire for 5 to 8 minutes and after it cools, strain this decoction and add a tablespoon of honey and another of vinegar, it is gargle with this decoction 2 or 3 times a day.%</item>
        <item>Nombre:Conjunctivitis# Descripcion:It is the inflammation of the conjunctival layer, the mucous membrane that lines the inside of the eyelids and that extends to the anterior part of the eyeball.# Remedios:Pour into a container half of 1 liter of water with 3 Vicarious Flowers, for a time, 2 or 3 hours) and then apply compresses 3 times a day.% Also Infusion of Black Tea, not hard boil the tea and let it rest, cool it and put fomentation for 3 minutes 3 times a day.</item>
        <item>Nombre:Gingivitis# Descripcion: It is a generally bacterial oral disease that causes inflammation and bleeding of the gums, caused by food debris that is trapped between the teeth.# Remedios:Apply Romerillo tincture on the affected parts% Take a bunch of Watercress Leaves and Stems, wash them well and then chew for a while. Also as a mouthwash it supports bleeding gums.% The sprout of Avocado Leaves, Blackberry, Chamomile and Vicaria, can also be used as a mouthwash for bleeding gums.</item>
        <item>Nombre:Flatulence, Gases# Descripcion: The mixture comes from ingested gases and other gases produced, from food, by bacteria and symbiotic yeasts# Remedios:Chamomile, mint or star anise infusions are very good.%</item>
        <item>Nombre:Fibroids# Descripcion:A myoma is a benign and non-cancerous tumor that grows in the muscular tissue of the uterus or myometrium in women. The appearance and growth of the fibroid is favored by estrogens, which is why its presentation occurs in the fertile age of the woman. Most fibroids have no symptoms. On the other hand, sometimes even small fibroids located in the endometrium can cause significant metrorrhagia and / or hypermenorrhea and thus, sometimes even cause anemia.# Remedios: Find a bunch of stems and leaves of the anamu plant, wash it well to remove impurities, then crush it in a blender to extract as much juice or juice as possible. You drink a cup of coffee on an empty stomach and another at night. The duration of treatment will depend on the situation of each patient.%</item>
        <item>Nombre:Hepatic cirrhosis# Descripcion:Cirrhosis is the end result of chronic liver damage caused by chronic liver disease.# Remedios: For this condition we recommend aloe vera. First, we must wash the Aloe Vera well, the thorns are removed, it is cut into small portions and these small portions are introduced into a jug with drinking water. This watery maceration is taken in the morning, a cup every day. % We can also use the Anamú. To do this, take a good bunch of Anamú leaves and stems, boil it in a container containing a liter of water, put it on a low heat for 5 to 8 minutes, then strain it. This decoction is taken as common water.</item>
        <item>Nombre: Hiccups or singult attacks# Descripcion:Hiccups are a repetitive, involuntary, spasmodic contraction of the diaphragm and intercostal muscles that causes a sudden inspiration of air. It can present in the form of a prolonged attack or recurrent attacks lasting longer than 48 hours. # Remedios:To face the hiccups, a decoction with 2 or 3 Cress leaves is prepared, they are previously divided and poured into half a liter of water and sipped. % Linden is also effective in suppressing hiccups, a decoction is prepared with the leaves of this plant. A decoction is prepared with leaves and stems of Eucalyptus and the vapors that emanate contribute to eradicate hiccups. Slowly drink a glass of water.</item>
        <item>Nombre: Lymphangitis# Descripcion: It is a type of inflammation that attacks the lymph nodes. Less commonly, it is caused by a staph infection. The infection causes the lymphatic vessels to become inflamed.Lymphangitis can be a sign of a worsening skin infection. The bacteria can spread into the bloodstream and cause life-threatening problems. For this condition there is a remedy that can be done at home and causes considerable relief.# Remedios:Avocado, a natural remedy for lymphangitis, consists of looking for a bunch of avocado leaves; boil this bunch in the equivalent of a bottle of water for 8 to 10 minutes and after it cools it is strained with an antiseptic cloth, packaged in a glass bottle -preferably in an amber bottle- and drink, at least , 4 glasses a day as common water. Simultaneously, several avocado leaves are placed on ice or in the freezer to cool them well, a kind of compress or poultice is prepared with them, which is located on the injured part of the extremities for at least 2 or 3 hours. The treatment is repeated daily until the inflammation disappears.</item>
        <item>Nombre: Aphonia or dysphonia# Descripcion:It is the medical term used to refer to the inability to speak. # Remedios:Place a piece of nutmeg inside a glass with drinking water, keep it at rest for an hour and at the end of that period that aqueous maceration is ingested, either half or all of the water contained in the glass. Afterwards, he replenishes the water where the piece of nutmeg is found. From then on, you drink that water whenever you want.% There is also another option is to boil in a container that contains a liter of water, a bunch of tender leaves of pigeon peas for 8 to 10 minutes, strain. Take 3 times a day a cup of coffee with milk, preferably warm.</item>
        <item>Nombre: Bronchial asthma# Descripcion:Pulmonary disease characterized by reversible airway obstruction, with airway inflammation and increased responsiveness to various stimuli.# Remedios:Prepare smoothie with equal parts honey and aloe vera. Store it in the refrigerator; where it won‘t freeze, in an amber bottle. Discard the mixture every 10 days. Take two tablespoons twice a day.%</item>
        <item>Nombre:Osteochondritis, Sternocostal Chondritis# Descripcion:It is pain in the cartilage that join the ribs with the sternum (flat bone located in the central part of the chest) and that represents a relatively common problem in young people and adults, while rare in children under 10 years of age.# Remedios:Make a decoction with two Chaya leaves, two aniseed Caisimon leaves, a linden sprig, boil in a liter of water for 8 to 10 min, strain it and drink as common water.</item>
        <item>Nombre:Vulvar moniliasis# Descripcion:Fungal infection in the vagina and the tissues of the opening of the vagina (vulva). This type of fungal infection is caused by a fungus called candida. This condition can cause swelling, severe itching, and a thick, white discharge from the vagina.# Remedios:One of the options used for this condition is the White Strenna or Campanilla. A decoction or decoction is prepared, boiling in a container that contains a liter of water a good bunch of leaves and stems of these plants. It is simmered for 8 to 10 minutes after it cools, strained and packaged in a previously sterilized container, which will be kept in a cool place or in the least cold part of the refrigerator. Vaginal washes are carried out with this decoction, using an expert if possible. These washes will be done every other day in a period spanning 10 days. % Another option is to ask pharmacies that sell Natural Medicine for a bottle of 10 percent propolis, applied topically, that is, externally, once a day to the affected areas of the vulva.</item>
        <item>Nombre:Toothache# Descripcion:Toothache is pain around the jaw or face. Usually the cause is a problem with a tooth. The cause of toothache can be irritation of a nerve at the root, infection, cavities, or loss of a tooth.# Remedios:Clove contains essential oils and acids, including eugenol, which contains analgesic and anesthetic properties. You just have to apply the nail on the tooth, or you can also buy the oil in health food stores, place a few drops on a cotton ball and gently rub the area.% Salt water mouthwash. It is one of the home remedies most recommended by dentists to relieve pain and reduce inflammation of the gums. You just need to add two teaspoons of salt to a cup of warm water, rinse your mouth with this mixture, and then spit it out. Mouth rinse with hydrogen peroxide, produces the same benefits as the previous solution; additionally, it kills bacteria, reduces plaque and helps heal bleeding gums. You must mix a little hydrogen peroxide at 3% with an equal part of water, rinse the mouth and then throw it away. Peppermint oil is one of the most used home remedies for decades to relieve toothache. Peppermint contains antibacterial properties that help reduce toothache, making it an excellent option for pain relief while seeking the care of a dental professional.% Garlic has numerous health-beneficial properties, such as circulation and fluid elimination. It also fights infections of the respiratory system and is a great ally against toothache.% Like garlic, onion is another natural antibiotic. Put a piece of onion in the area of ​​the teeth or gums to relieve pain. Another of the formulas to prevent oral diseases is to chew an onion for three minutes a day, although it is not very pleasant and can cause bad odors. It is important to rinse the mouth afterwards.</item>
        <item>Nombre:Hematuria# Descripcion:Hematuria is the presence of blood in the urine. It can be visible to the naked eye or microscopically. It can be caused by a bleeding disorder or by certain medications, or by stones, infections, or tumors. It may be due to injury to the kidneys, urinary tract, prostate, or genitalia.# Remedios:A decoction or decoction is prepared with a handful of shells or bark from the trunk or thick branches of the Guásima forest, another made of Bomba fruit roots and a third of Guamá root. They are conveniently divided into small portions after washing them thoroughly with water. These bunches are poured into a container containing four liters of water and simmered for 20 minutes until the decoction takes on a reddish hue. After filtering it with an antiseptic cloth, it is packaged and stored in the cold. This decoction is taken as common water. Treatment is carried out for 21 days. During this period you should not drink coffee or alcoholic or aromatic beverages. During breakfast it is necessary to drink a glass of coconut water accompanied with the juice or juice of a lemon slice.</item>
        <item>Nombre:Cardiac ischemia# Descripcion:Myocardial ischemia, also called cardiac ischemia, reduces the ability of the heart muscle to pump blood. A sudden and severe blockage of one of the arteries of the heart can lead to a heart attack.# Remedios:It is made in the form of maceration with honey and garlic, in the following proportion. 350 grams of honey and 250 grams of well crushed garlic. Honey and garlic are mixed and everything is left to rest for seven days. The dosage consists of ingesting one tablespoon forty minutes before meals for two months.</item>
        <item>Nombre:Jaundice# Descripcion:Jaundice is a yellow discoloration of the skin, mucous membranes, or eyes. It can occur if the liver cannot efficiently process red blood cells as they break down. It is normal in healthy newborns and usually goes away on its own. In older people, it can be a sign of infection or liver disease.# Remedios:In a traditional way, many people face this condition in Cuba, making a decoction or decoction using a bunch of leaves, stems and roots of the plant known as Grama. That bunch is thoroughly washed and poured into a container containing one liter of water. It is placed in the candle, over low heat for 8 to 10 minutes until it boils. After it cools down, strain it. The dosage is to ingest an eight-ounce glass twice a day (in the morning and before bed).</item>
        <item>Nombre:Inflammation of the duodenum or duodenitis# Descripcion:Duodenitis is an inflammation of the duodenum or the first part of the small intestine, which is located just below the stomach. Both gastritis and duodenitis have the same causes and treatments. Both disorders can occur in men and women, as well as in people of all ages.# Remedios: According to traditional practices, a treatment is carried out for 21 consecutive days, as follows. Find a bunch of leaves and stems of nightshade, it is known in some areas of the country as joruro, pour it into a container containing half a liter of water, boil for 10 minutes over low heat. Then the decoction is filtered and one cup is taken on an empty stomach and another before going to bed for five consecutive days and for the next five days, half a cup is taken in the morning and another half at night. At the end of this period, the treatment is restarted, but with the decoction or cooking for five days a little cup, concludes with the ingestion of the last six days of half a cup of the juice that is prepared with the leaves and stems of blackberry, according to the practices they do not present contraindications.</item>
        <item>Nombre:Broncoestasia# Descripcion:A condition that damages the airways of the lungs and makes it difficult to pass mucus. Bronchiectasis can develop from an infection or a medical disorder, such as pneumonia and cystic fibrosis. The mucosa builds up and allows bacteria to grow, causing frequent infections. # Remedies: Find a bunch of leaves and stem of oregano from the ground, two or three leaves of aloe (the peel is removed and left in the glass or pomp), a piece of the stem of the trunk of a banana plant, a bunch of leaves and copal stem, a manajú ​​branch (the thorns are removed), 20 majagua flowers, five yagrumas leaves, and half a liter of pure honey, they are washed well, fragmented into small portions and put to boil in two and a half liters of water for 15 minutes, turn off, strain and then add the honey from the bees and pass through the blender, put it in a glass container, keep it in the refrigerator and the adults they should take two to three ounces, three times a day.</item>
    </array>
    <array name="files">
        <item>cebolla</item>
        <item>ajo</item>
        <item>sabila</item>
        <item>eneldo</item>
        <item>bija</item>
        <item>pimiento</item>
        <item>calendula</item>
        <item>guacamayafrancesa</item>
        <item>canhafistula</item>
        <item>canhandonga</item>
        <item>calabaza</item>
        <item>canhasanta</item>
        <item>eucaliptolimon</item>
        <item>hinojo</item>
        <item>flordejamaica</item>
        <item>jazmindeespanha</item>
        <item>tilo</item>
        <item>manzanilla</item>
        <item>mentajaponesa</item>
        <item>hierbabuena</item>
        <item>noni</item>
        <item>berro</item>
        <item>albahacablanca</item>
        <item>oregano</item>
        <item>albahacamorada</item>
        <item>mejorana</item>
        <item>tederinhon</item>
        <item>caisimondeanis</item>
        <item>llantenmenor</item>
        <item>llanten</item>
        <item>copal</item>
        <item>guayaba</item>
        <item>manglerojo</item>
        <item>romero</item>
        <item>ruda</item>
        <item>salviadecastilla</item>
        <item>jenjibre</item>
        <item>guanabana</item>
        <item>cardosanto</item>
        <item>pinhaderaton</item>
        <item>artemisa</item>
        <item>romerillo</item>
        <item>escobaamarga</item>
        <item>aguacate</item>
        <item>buganvilla</item>
        <item>anamu</item>
        <item>guira</item>
        <item>magueymorado</item>
        <item>mango</item>
        <item>neem</item>
        <item>dormidera</item>
        <item>bejucoubi</item>
        <item>cundeamor</item>
        <item>lavanda</item>
        <item>pasiflora</item>
        <item>valeriana</item>
        <item>guanina</item>
        <item>yaya</item>
        <item>oreganodelatierra</item>
        <item>vicaria</item>
        <item>chancapiedra</item>
        <item>verbena</item>
        <item>verdolaga</item>
        <item>nitro</item>
        <item>limon</item>
        <item>coco</item>
        <item>chaya</item>
        <item>apasote</item>
        <item>zarzaparilla</item>
        <item>chichicaste</item>
        <item>guisazodecaballo</item>
        <item>marpacifico</item>
        <item>canutillo</item>
        <item>yerbamora</item>
        <item>canhamexicana</item>
        <item>moringa</item>
        <item>doradilla</item>
        <item>sasafras</item>
        <item>remolacha</item>
        <item>nuezmoscada</item>
        <item>cilantro</item>
        <item>anisestrellado</item>
        <item>boldo</item>
        <item>anilcimarron</item>
        <item>naranjaagria</item>
        <item>alancrancillo</item>
        <item>siempreviva</item>
        <item>rabodegato</item>
        <item>esclaviosa</item>
        <item>tuatua</item>
        <item>bledoblanco</item>
        <item>paraiso</item>
        <item>marilope</item>
        <item>alcanfor</item>
        <item>arraigan</item>
        <item>gavilan</item>
        <item>guasima</item>
        <item>higuereta</item>
        <item>majagua</item>
        <item>maravilla</item>
        <item>vetiver</item>
        <item>arraclan</item>
        <item>guayuyo</item>
        <item>guiritodepasion</item>
        <item>guaguasi</item>
        <item>capuchina</item>
        <item>dagame</item>
        <item>grama</item>
        <item>yagruma</item>
        <item>reseda</item>
        <item>jubaban</item>
        <item>maranhon</item>
        <item>jobo</item>
        <item>apio</item>
        <item>curujey</item>
        <item>almacigo</item>
        <item>cucaracha</item>
        <item>pinhonbotija</item>
        <item>flordemuerto</item>
        <item>espinacademalabar</item>
        <item>yerbadelasangre</item>
        <item>pinomacho</item>
        <item>agrimonia</item>
        <item>guayacan</item>
        <item>trebol</item>
        <item>orozuz</item>
        <item>quitadolor</item>
        <item>malvate</item>
        <item>escobilla</item>
        <item>varia</item>
        <item>salviadeplaya</item>
        <item>sagu</item>
        <item>yamagua</item>
        <item>siguaraya</item>
    </array>
    <array name="preparaciones_frecuentes">
        <item>Nombre:Infusion# Descripción:It is one of the most common home ways to use medicinal plants. The preparation consists of leaving the plant in contact with boiling water for a few minutes. In general, infusions of leaves and flowers are prepared that easily yield their components to hot water, as they are not woody. In addition to being taken as water for time, the infusions are used to make other preparations such as compresses, baths, gargles, etc. We must always cover the cup during the time of contact of the plant with the water, to avoid that the medicinal substances are lost with the steam. Do not keep the infusion for more than one day, therefore it is preferable to use it immediately. To prepare it, 2 teaspoons of the plant should be placed in a cup. Add boiling water. Cover and let stand 10 minutes. Sweeten to taste and drink.</item>
        <item>Nombre:Decoction# Descripción:It is made by boiling the plant with water. Plants with a woody structure (thick stems, bark, roots) are generally prepared in this way. To prepare it, 2 teaspoons of the crumbled plant should be placed in a sturdy container. Add 2 cups of water. Heat to a boil and keep simmering for 5 to 10 minutes.</item>
        <item>Nombre:Reduction# Descripción:If cooking is carried out for more than 20 minutes, the reduction occurs. It is used for active principles that resist heat and which require a higher concentration due to their low proportion.</item>
        <item>Nombre:Maceration# Descripción: It consists of letting the fresh, non-dried plants rest in cold water for a few hours (10 to 12 hours). It is used to extract active ingredients that are unstable in the face of heat, but soluble in water (for example, the active ingredients of red mangrove for gastric ulcers).</item>
        <item>Nombre:Concentrated# Descripción:The extracts can be prepared as soft fluids or dry fluids. They can be aqueous extracts, in which the parts of the plant in question are introduced into water for 15 or 30 days; or hydroalcoholic extracts, where a mixture of water (70%) and alcohol (30%) is used, for 30 days.</item>
        <item>Nombre:Tincture or medicinal wines# Descripción:They are obtained by leaving the plant in contact with a mixture of alcohol and water for 7 days. It is a preparation that allows a greater concentration of the medicinal plant, but its preparation requires care. It is taken from 20 to 40 drops at a time, it is also used to prepare infusions. To prepare it, you should place 2 cups (100 gr) of crumbled fresh plant in a jar with a lid. Add a liter of 60º or 80º alcohol; if not, you can use cane brandy; cover and shake well for 10 minutes. Leave in contact (maceration) for 7 days, shaking frequently. Filter with a clean cloth, in a funnel. Store in a tightly closed bottle protected from light. Label with the data of the date of preparation.</item>
        <item>Nombre:Elixir# Descripción:Tincture or medicinal wines</item>
        <item>Nombre:Juices; Juices # Descripción: It is always obtained from fresh plants, in these are found, almost without any alteration, all the components of the plant. It should be drunk at the time of its preparation because they decompose quickly. To prepare it, the necessary amount of plant must be washed. Place in a container and mash it well. Filter and strain; then extract the juice by placing the paste obtained on a clean canvas and squeezing it vigorously. Receive the liquid in a clean container.</item>
        <item>Nombre:Syrups# Descripción: They are prepared by extracting the active components of the plant with water and subsequently adding sugar, which is a flavoring and preservative agent. Its pleasant taste covers the bitter taste of some plants and facilitates its administration to children. To prepare it, place a cup (50 gr) of plant in a small pot with a lid. Add 112 liters of boiling water on the plant. Cover and let stand for 15 minutes. Strain with a canvas to obtain the liquid. Add little by little and stirring 3 1/2 cups (850 g) of sugar in the infusion obtained. Take the mixture to a bain-marie (the container that contains the mixture goes into a larger one with water and over the fire or stove) to subject it to gentle heat. Shake constantly for approximately 30 minutes, until a viscous liquid is obtained (we must obtain a liter of syrup). Strain the syrup using a very fine mesh strainer. Store the preparation in a sterilized amber (caramel-colored) bottle. It is important that the jar is completely filled and tightly capped. 4 drops of alcohol should be added to the bottle before closing it, to avoid contamination of the surface.</item>
        <item>Nombre:Medicinal oils# Descripción: Like alcohol, oil is another of the most widely used solvents. There are certain plants that better transfer their active ingredients to the oil. They are the most used preparations for external use.</item>
        <item>Nombre:Poultices# Descripción:The crushed plant is applied directly to the affected area, they are generally non-woody parts. Many times, instead of crushing the plant, the veins are removed from the leaves and, once clean, they are applied directly to the skin. Poultices can also be made with dried herbs, mixing them with boiled water and making a paste that is applied at a suitable temperature. To prepare it, a sufficient quantity of plant must be collected and washed well. Blend it until you get a homogeneous paste. Apply to the affected area covering with a cloth and holding with a tape.</item>
        <item>Nombre:Compresses# Descripción:A much more concentrated infusion or cooking is used than for direct use. In the infusion or cooking of the hot plant, a very clean cloth is wetted. Apply to the affected area taking great care that the temperature of the cloth can be tolerated by the skin.</item>
        <item>Nombre:Inhalations# Descripción:The water vapor that contains the medicinal substances of the plant is used. To prepare it, a handful (5 g) of plant must be placed in a container. Add a liter of boiling water. Immediately, place the head on the vapors that emanate from the container, covering completely with a towel. Be careful not to burn yourself. Breathe in the vapors emanating deeply and exhale them slowly. Then rest, do not expose yourself to cold drafts.</item>
        <item>Nombre:Horchatas# Descripción: Drinks that are made from almonds or some oil seeds and fruits crushed with water and sugar.</item>
        <item>Nombre:Bath# Descripción:They consist of totally or partially immersing the body in an infusion of the plant. They are indicated for hemorrhoids and vaginal conditions, among others. Prepare one or more liters of an infusion or concentrated cooking of the plant. Place it in a bathtub filled with warm water and mix. Immerse yourself in the prepared water.</item>
        <item>Nombre:Soaps# Descripción:Plants that have an anti-infective or anti-inflammatory effect are used to heal pimples, wounds or other skin diseases. Various parts of the plant will be used such as leaves, flowers, roots, husks, etc. To prepare it, you must take a bar of neutral soap, grated or minced very finely. Chop or cut two cups of washed plant. Cook the plant for 15 or 20 minutes, let it cool and strain the cooking. We put it back on a low heat and add the soap slowly, stirring until we get a cream. We remove from the heat and put in a mold until it hardens (1 or 2 days). We remove from the mold, cut into pieces according to criteria, wrap in plastic or other protective paper and place your label.</item>
        <item>Nombre:Ointments# Descripción:Formerly they were prepared based on animal fats of pork, beef or chicken infusion. Popularly used until today, these have the disadvantage that the preparations obtained cannot be kept for too long, because they decompose and rancid (spoil) quickly. For this reason, it is advisable to use vegetable shortening or solid petroleum jelly to obtain a higher quality product. They will keep longer if we first prepare a tincture of the medicinal plant and then add it to the fats in a water bath. To prepare it, 100 gr of the selected plant must be weighed. Place a kilo of petroleum jelly or vegetable shortening in a cast iron pot. Melt in a water bath and add the plant. Mix for an hour keeping in a water bath. Strain hot using a strainer or canvas. Let cool and pack in a wide-mouth pot, with a lid, and label with the indications of its preparation date.</item>
    </array>
    <array name="terminos">
        <item>Abortive</item>
        <item>Skin conditions</item>
        <item>Kidney disease</item>
        <item>Respiratory conditions</item>
        <item>Cold sores</item>
        <item>Analgesic</item>
        <item>Anginas</item>
        <item>Angina pectoris</item>
        <item>Antianemic</item>
        <item>Anti-asthmatic</item>
        <item>Antibacterial</item>
        <item>Anticatarrhal</item>
        <item>Anticholleric</item>
        <item>Antidiarrheal</item>
        <item>Antiscorbutic</item>
        <item>Antispasmodic</item>
        <item>Antifungal</item>
        <item>Anthelmintic</item>
        <item>Antihemorrhoidal</item>
        <item>Anti-infective</item>
        <item>Anti-inflammatory</item>
        <item>Antilipemic</item>
        <item>Antifungal</item>
        <item>Antimicrobial</item>
        <item>Antipyretic</item>
        <item>Anti-rheumatic</item>
        <item>Antiseptic</item>
        <item>Anti-syphilitic</item>
        <item>Antithrombotic</item>
        <item>Cough suppressant</item>
        <item>Antiulcer</item>
        <item>Antiviral</item>
        <item>Stroke</item>
        <item>Arthritis</item>
        <item>Astringent</item>
        <item>Bactericidal</item>
        <item>Bronchodilator</item>
        <item>Carcinoma</item>
        <item>Cardiocirculatory</item>
        <item>Carminative</item>
        <item>Headache</item>
        <item>Healing</item>
        <item>Colagogo</item>
        <item>Choleretic</item>
        <item>Kidney colic</item>
        <item>Colic</item>
        <item>Conjunctiva</item>
        <item>Conjunctivitis</item>
        <item>Debugging</item>
        <item>Dermatology</item>
        <item>Unclogging</item>
        <item>Diabetes</item>
        <item>Diarrhea</item>
        <item>Digestive</item>
        <item>Dysentery</item>
        <item>Dysmenorrhea</item>
        <item>Diuretic</item>
        <item>Drastic</item>
        <item>Emenagogues</item>
        <item>Emetocathartic</item>
        <item>Emollient</item>
        <item>Stimulants</item>
        <item>Stomatitis</item>
        <item>Expectorant</item>
        <item>Excerpts</item>
        <item>Febrifugal</item>
        <item>Intermittent fever</item>
        <item>Gingivitis</item>
        <item>Hemorrhage</item>
        <item>Hepatic</item>
        <item>Hypotensive</item>
        <item>Inflammation</item>
        <item>Laxative</item>
        <item>Lymphangitis</item>
        <item>Litholytic</item>
        <item>Lumbago</item>
        <item>Nephritic</item>
        <item>Neuralgia</item>
        <item>Ophthalmias</item>
        <item>Paralysis</item>
        <item>Chest</item>
        <item>Burns</item>
        <item>Renal</item>
        <item>Repanda</item>
        <item>Resolutive</item>
        <item>Respiratory</item>
        <item>Rheumatism</item>
        <item>Sedative or sedative</item>
        <item>Syncarpal</item>
        <item>Sufrutescence</item>
        <item>Tincture</item>
        <item>Tonic</item>
        <item>Topic</item>
        <item>Ulcers</item>
        <item>Urinary</item>
        <item>Warts</item>
        <item>Vertigos</item>
        <item>Vulnerary</item>
    </array>
    <array name="terminos_explicaciones">
        <item>That it has the property of aborting or damaging the fetus.</item>
        <item>Skin diseases.</item>
        <item>Enfermedades del riñón.</item>
        <item>Diseases of the respiratory tract</item>
        <item>Little sores in the mouth.</item>
        <item>Pain reliever medicine.</item>
        <item>Name given to inflammations of the pharynx.</item>
        <item>Short-term heart disease, with death anguish and violent pain from the sternum to the shoulder, arm, forearm and left hand.</item>
        <item>That prevents or fights the lack of red blood cells in the blood.</item>
        <item>That prevents or fights asthma.</item>
        <item>Drug that acts against diseases caused by bacteria.</item>
        <item>That prevents or fights colds.</item>
        <item>That avoids cholera.</item>
        <item>That fights or avoids frequent diarrhea.</item>
        <item>That fights or prevents the disease caused by the lack of vitamin C.</item>
        <item>Own medications to combat spasms or seizures.</item>
        <item>That fights diseases caused by fungi.</item>
        <item>Which is used to fight intestinal worms.</item>
        <item>Which is used to fight hemorrhoids.</item>
        <item>That prevents or prevents infections.</item>
        <item>That fights or prevents tissue swelling.</item>
        <item>That reduces the presence of fats in the blood.</item>
        <item>Which acts against fungi.</item>
        <item>Drug that acts against diseases produced by different types of pathogenic microorganisms.</item>
        <item>Medicine that lowers fever.</item>
        <item>It is said of the drugs that it is used to combat rheumatism.</item>
        <item>Used to disinfect.</item>
        <item>That acts against syphilis.</item>
        <item>Action against total or partial obstruction of the vessels.</item>
        <item>Medicine that fights or prevents coughing.</item>
        <item>That prevents the formation of ulcers.</item>
        <item>That fights or avoids viruses.</item>
        <item>Spill of blood in the brain that determines the sudden suspension of brain function.</item>
        <item>Inflammation of the joints.</item>
        <item>Drug that reduces the size of tissues; it is used as an antonym for laxative.</item>
        <item>That kills bacteria.</item>
        <item>Dilator of the bronchi.</item>
        <item>The atypical forms of epithelial tumors are grouped under this name; it comprises most of the neoplasms commonly called cancers.</item>
        <item>That helps the circulation of blood through the heart.</item>
        <item>That fight intestinal gas.</item>
        <item>Headache.</item>
        <item>That heals or closes a wound.</item>
        <item>That stimulates the secretion of bile.</item>
        <item>Said of the substances that increase bile secretion.</item>
        <item>Sharp pain in the kidneys.</item>
        <item>Colic A disease characterized by violent contractions of the intestines.</item>
        <item>Mucous membrane that lines the inside of the eyelid.</item>
        <item>Inflammation of the conjunctiva membrane of the eyes.</item>
        <item>That serves to purify the blood.</item>
        <item>Science that studies skin diseases.</item>
        <item>Medicines that make intestinal blockages go away.</item>
        <item>Pancreas disease that is manifested by an excess of glucose in the blood and its presence in the urine.</item>
        <item>Morbid phenomenon that consists of liquid and frequent evacuations through the rectum.</item>
        <item>That helps digestion.</item>
        <item>Disease characterized by painful and chronic diarrhea.</item>
        <item>Difficult and painful menstruation.</item>
        <item>That it has virtues to facilitate the excretion of urine.</item>
        <item>Very energetic and irritating purgatives.</item>
        <item>Medications that activate menstruation in women.</item>
        <item>Medications that act both as vomiting and purgative.</item>
        <item>They serve to soften tumors and reduce inflammation.</item>
        <item>Remedies that have the power to promote a more or less pronounced excitement or stimulation throughout the metabolism.</item>
        <item>Name applied to the set of diseases of the oral cavity.</item>
        <item>What makes you expectorate, that is, spitting up secretions from the respiratory system.</item>
        <item>Concentrated substances that are extracted from the meat of flowers, leaves and other parts of medicinal plants.</item>
        <item>That serve to cut or reduce fevers.</item>
        <item>Symptoms that are manifested by the speed of the pulsations and the increase in temperature, which is interrupted or ceases and then returns.</item>
        <item>Infectious disease that causes inflammation of the gums.</item>
        <item>Abnormal flow of blood from any part of the body</item>
        <item>Pertaining to the liver.</item>
        <item>Drug that lowers blood pressure.</item>
        <item>Increase in the size of the tissues. Swelling from fluid build-up</item>
        <item>Medicine to move the belly.</item>
        <item>Inflammation of the lymphatic vessels.</item>
        <item>That destroys the stones in the bladder.</item>
        <item>Rheumatic pain that is suffered in the waist.</item>
        <item>Which refers to the kidneys.</item>
        <item>Pain in a nerve.</item>
        <item>Eye disease</item>
        <item>Nerve center disease, causing paralysis of the limbs</item>
        <item>That is used to cure a cough.</item>
        <item>Effect caused by fire or corrosive substances on living tissue.</item>
        <item>Of the kidneys.</item>
        <item>Bent over, crooked.</item>
        <item>Which has the virtue of dissolving or dissipating tumors (see emollient).</item>
        <item>That serves for breathing or facilitates it.</item>
        <item>Disease characterized by joint or muscle pain.</item>
        <item>Which has the virtue of calming or soothing.</item>
        <item>Set of fruits welded together, from a single flower. Also concrescent fruits originated in different flowers.</item>
        <item>Small plant similar to a tree.</item>
        <item>Concentrated solution of a medicinal plant.</item>
        <item>It is applied to drugs that tone or fortify the body in general or some organs.</item>
        <item>External drug.</item>
        <item>Infected wound or sore.</item>
        <item>Relating to urine.</item>
        <item>Small skin growths.</item>
        <item>Dizziness, sudden and temporary embarrassment of the judgment. Height disorder.</item>
        <item>Drug that is used in the external healing of bumps, wounds and ulcers.</item>
    </array>
</resources>